<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The bramble berry: or, A briefe discourse touching participating in mixt assemblies at the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, wherein is most full and cleare satisfaction given to every weak and doubting Christian, both by testimony out of Gods Word, and many invincible reasons and arguments for that purpose, grounded upon the same, wherein is first principally discussed and resolved these three maine questions following: I. Whether the Congregationall assemblies in England be true churches of Jesus Christ, yea or no?  2. Whether it be lawfull to participate at the Sacrament of the Lords Supper among carnall and prophane men?  3. Whether the admitting of ungodly men to the table of the Lord be sufficient warrant for ministers to desist the publike administration of the Sacrament, or for particular members to decline it, or separate themselves? Secondarily, briefe and satisfactory answers given to all the principall places of Scripture alleadged to maintaine a separation from our church assemblies, besides their arguments and allegations sufficiently resolved: set forth for the benefit of the tender conscience. By W. L. a faithfull petitioner and carefull practitioner for the peace and welfare of the church and people of God.</title>
            <author>W. L., a faithful petitioner and careful practitioner for the peace and welfare of the church and people of God.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88870</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L84</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E56_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R413</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872608</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872608</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155268</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88870)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155268)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 10:E56[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The bramble berry: or, A briefe discourse touching participating in mixt assemblies at the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, wherein is most full and cleare satisfaction given to every weak and doubting Christian, both by testimony out of Gods Word, and many invincible reasons and arguments for that purpose, grounded upon the same, wherein is first principally discussed and resolved these three maine questions following: I. Whether the Congregationall assemblies in England be true churches of Jesus Christ, yea or no?  2. Whether it be lawfull to participate at the Sacrament of the Lords Supper among carnall and prophane men?  3. Whether the admitting of ungodly men to the table of the Lord be sufficient warrant for ministers to desist the publike administration of the Sacrament, or for particular members to decline it, or separate themselves? Secondarily, briefe and satisfactory answers given to all the principall places of Scripture alleadged to maintaine a separation from our church assemblies, besides their arguments and allegations sufficiently resolved: set forth for the benefit of the tender conscience. By W. L. a faithfull petitioner and carefull practitioner for the peace and welfare of the church and people of God.</title>
                  <author>W. L., a faithful petitioner and careful practitioner for the peace and welfare of the church and people of God.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 54, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Richard Cotes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 26".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155268:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BRAMBLE BERRY: OR, A briefe diſcourſe touching participating in mixt Aſſemblies at the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, wherein is moſt full and cleare ſatisfaction given to every weak and doubting Chriſtian, both by teſtimony out of Gods Word, and many invincible reaſons and arguments for that purpoſe, grounded upon the ſame, wherein is firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally diſcuſſed and reſolved theſe three maine Queſtions following:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Whether the Congregationall Aſſemblies in</hi> England <hi>be true Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, yea or no?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Whether it be lawfull to participate at the Sacrament of the Lords Supper among carnall and prophane men?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Whether the admitting of ungodly men to the Table of the Lord be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent warrant for Miniſters to deſiſt the publike adminiſtration of the Sacrament, or for particular members to decline it, or ſeparate themſelves?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>SECONDARILY, Briefe and ſatisfactory anſwers given to all the principall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture alleadged to maintaine a ſeparation from our Church Aſſemblies, beſides their arguments and alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations ſufficiently reſolved: ſet forth for the benefit of the tender conſcience.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. L.</hi> a faithfull petitioner and carefull practitioner for the peace and welfare of the Church and people of God.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Richard Cotes.</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:155268:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155268:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader, when I had the firſt occaſion to enter upon this Subject, by the requeſt of ſome Chriſtian friends to whom I was enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by way of promiſe to deliver my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I did neither thinke to have waded ſo farre into it as I was afterward neceſsitated for ſatisfaction both of my ſelfe and them; nor that ſuch peeced and unpoliſhed lines ſhould ever have cumbred the Preſſe: But after the delivery of it, being deſired to give Copies to divers friends, I found the writing both tedious and chargeable, which together with other importunings, and the deſire I have fully to ſatisfie ſuch as deſire ſatisfaction in this point with as much eaſe, and as little charge as may be, prevailed with me to bring that to publike ſight, for which I may meete with private cenſure; but knowing the moſt pious and learned indeavours that ever yet ſaw the Sunne have beene obnoxious to cenſorious humours, I wave that: the Lord knowing that my principall aime herein is the glory of God and the peace and concord of his Church and people in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring the uniting of the affections and opinions of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which in theſe times of diſtraction are ſo divided in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the point of mixt participation at the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, it being an Ordinance of ſo high concernement: and indeed the diverſity of opinions in and about this and other parts of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s worſhip, even in godly men, is the maine ground and Baſes upon which not onely Papiſts and Jeſuites and others of that Romiſh rabble would build that great difference that is fallen betweene his Majeſty and Parliament, and make the very cauſe of all the rapines,
<pb facs="tcp:155268:3"/> ruines, plunderings, and bloudſheds in the Kingdome; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut even our carnall Goſpellers, Neuters, and Luke-warme Profeſſors, yea our Athiſticall and Prophane wretches goe hand in hand with them in this ſcandalous straine, as if the great Councell of the Kingdome were led by ſome factious private ſpirit. And although it be nothing ſo indeed, yet too many at this day are ſo impious as to charge it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, not thinking that in wounding that Aſſembly of our Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amentary Worthies they ſtrike at the heart of Religion, Law, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, life, and poſterity, and all that we can account precious in this life: we cannot be ignorant how the eares of Gods people are daily filled from the mouthes of that Antichriſtian crew with theſe and ſuch like expreſsions: We wonder why the Parliament ſettles not Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the government of the Church, there is now ſo many Religions a man cannot tell which to be of; theſe Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans, and Roundheads, are the cauſe of all theſe troubles: one will have no Divine ſervice, another no Lords Prayer, another he will not come to the Sacrament becauſe of the wicked there, nay theſe Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan Preachers are worſt of all, and the like. And albeit a man might eaſily anſwer theſe and many more ſuch fooliſh allegations which if God permit I ſhall indeavour in my next meditations for publike not being able to heare the cauſe of God wounded, and be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, leſt the very ſtones ſhould crie out upon the great neglect of ſuch unto whom more properly it belongs: yet I beleeve theſe men who ever they be that make this diſturbance in our publike Aſſemblies by ſinging downe Service, pulling Common prayer book and Surpleſſes out of the Readers hands and from his backe, keeping their Hats on in time of Common-prayer, withdrawing from the Sacrament becauſe carnall men are admitted, although in other reſpect they may be godly, yet by this their prepoſterous and blinde Zeale, for at the beſt it muſt be Zeale without knowledge, have done more hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to that great worke of Reformation, ſo much prayed by for all Gods people, and laboured for by that honourable Aſſembly of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, then all their indeavours otherwiſe can ever be able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote it, the enemies of true Religion taking great advantage by it,
<pb facs="tcp:155268:3"/> and the cauſe of Chriſt ſo much the more injured: the very Jeſuites themſelves not being able to hatch ſuch another ſtratagem for their purpoſe, for by this meanes all the neuters of the Kingdom are readier to ſide with them then thoſe that ſtand for the cauſe of God and the Kingdome, not that I goe about to plead for any corruption or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation in the Doctrine or Diſcipline of the Church, but doe ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire that men would waite upon God in the uſe of lawfull meanes till he ſhall be pleaſed to perfect the worke of Reformation by ſuch inſtruments as are lawfully called to it, and intruſted both by God and man with the great affaires of Church and State, and not every particular man to ſnatch the ſword out of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates hand, or be a ſeeming reformer, when indeed he is an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, not of order, but confuſion: But not intending to raiſe too large a Porch before ſuch a poore thatched Cottage, leſt the worke become more tedious then either toothſome or p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ofitable, I haſten, deſiring (the) good Reader not to expect here either Learning or Logick, but a plaine, and I hope profitable diſcourſe fitted to the meaneſt capacity, for whoſe ſakes my paines is principally ſpent upon it; neither would I have beene ſo eaſily prevailed upon to come to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, being a man of ſuch low abiliities, and having as little time as any, but that men of great parts whoſe whole life is or ought to be ſequeſtred from the world, doe either utterly forget, or wholly neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to ſpeake to a point of ſo great concernment, eſpecially in theſe times of ſo great diſtraction. What I have done herein the Lord of his mercy adde a bleſsing upon that, though the worke be meane and the Author deſpicable, yet God may have glory, and his Church and people benefit: And if any thing deare Chriſt an have fallen from my pen diſtaſtefull to the tender conſcience, I deſire it may be imputed to my weakneſſe, and want of time to make things more cleare, rather then want of affection to give ſatisfaction to ſuch a ſoule: for as the meditations are irretoricall and broken, ſo are the peeces a d patches of time ſpent upon them, as my calling would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. And to the end thou maieſt profit, I deſire thou wouldeſt have patience to reade it firſt once thorow by reaſon it is not ſo metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall
<pb facs="tcp:155268:4"/> as I could wiſh it, and afterward with more deliberation conſider: Secondly, that thou wouldeſt not receive prejudice at the meanneſſe of the Author, who intends thy good: And laſtly I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Lord to adde ſuch a bleſsing as may tend to his glory, the peace of his Church; and alſo thy particular ſatisfaction and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and I ſhall be encouraged to ingage my poore Talent for the like furture benefit.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord Jeſus, W. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155268:4"/>
            <head>A briefe diſcourſe touching participating in mixt Aſſemblies at the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, wherein is moſt full and cleare ſatisfaction and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution given to every weake and doubting Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; concerning theſe three Queſtions follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; to ſuch places of Scripture as ſeeme to maintaine a Separation from our Church Aſſemblies.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering there are many in this Kingdome, and in theſe dayes of diviſion and diſtraction, that queſtion the truth of the Church and Church Aſſemblies in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> or at leaſt the truth of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I have thought good by way of Introduction to that which I mainely intend, to wit, the ſecond Queſtion, Whether it be lawfull to participate in and among prophane and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men at the Sacrament of the Lords Supper; to ſpeake ſomething to the firſt, and onely ſo much as ſhall be requiſite to make way to the ſecond and third queſtion, which by Gods aſſiſtance I hope will ſatisfie the impartiall and indifferent Reader.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Firſt then concerning the truth of our Church Aſſemblies, that they are true Churches of Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
               <p>I lay downe this as an undeniable truth, that that Church or Church Aſſembly wherein the fundamentall truths of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt is truly taught, the Sacraments and Ordinances of Chriſt diſpenſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſufficient means offered to ſalvation, obtained and had, and a viſible profeſſion of obedience to the ſame, that is a true viſible Church of Chriſt, notwithſtanding there may be many corruptions in it, both in Doctrine and Diſcipline and members thereof.</p>
               <p>For the proofe hereof I propound the example of the Church of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> the Apoſtolike Churches of <hi>Corinth, Galatia,</hi> and alſo the the 7. Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſpoken of by Saint <hi>John, Revel. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ</hi> 4. all which are confeſſed by all to be true Churches of Chriſt, yet divers of them as corrupt as the Churches of <hi>England</hi> at this day both in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Diſcipline, and members: in one degree or other.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:155268:5"/>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>For the Church of the Jewes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 56.10. Mat. 23.16. Mat. 23.3. Mat. 15.14.</note>It was exceedingly corrupt in all three particulars, their Prieſts were ignorant, unlearned, vicious, and prophane, blinde leaders of the blinde; Chriſt therefore exhorts the people not to doe after their workes, but after their ſayings, for they ſaid and did not: very hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall binding heavy burthens upon others, but not touching them themſelves with their leaſt fingers, proud and ambitious, loving the uppermoſt ſeates in the Synagogues, and made broade their phylacta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, all what they did was to be ſeene of men: their callings was alſo corrupt, for whereas the high Prieſt by the Law ought to have held his Office for his life,<note place="margin">Exod 29.5 E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ek. 22.26</note> they choſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> every yeare, and according to our beſt expoſitors they bought and ſold the Office for money: they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo principall violaters of the Law of God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the people were generally notorious and prophane, for at <hi>Nazareth</hi> they were ſo evilly diſpoſed and ſo inraged againſt Chriſt, that they all roſe up to throw him headlong downe the hill whereon the City was built:<note place="margin">Luk 4 28.</note> See <hi>Caparnaum, Corazin,</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida,</hi> how the Lord Chriſt was againſt them for their impiety and infidelity,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.21 22.</note> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the great workes Chriſt had done among them: and as for <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 19.41</note> Chriſt beheld the City and wept over it, ſaying, <hi>Oh that in this thy day thou hadſt knowne the things that belong to thy peace!</hi> See alſo how they made havocke of the Lords Prophets, beating them, ſtoning them, &amp;c. and as for their affection to the Lord Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luke 23.19</note> they preferre <hi>Barrabas</hi> a thiefe and murtherer before him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Marke 7.8.9. Mat. 21.2.</note>Thirdly, for their worſhip, it was filled with ſuperſtitious Ceremonies and Traditions, and theſe they preferred before the commands of God, the Temple alſo was prophaned and made a denne of theeves, they bought and ſold Oxen, and Doves, and made it an exchange for coyne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">John 9.12 Mat. 15.4. Mat. 5.21. Mal. 1.8 Deut. 14.2.3. &amp; 29.10.11, 12. &amp; 7.6.7. Eſa. 1.2, 3, 4 10. Lam. 4.6.22. Ezek. 16.46.47.</note>Alſo their Diſcipline was exceedingly corrupt, for if any man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Jeſus to be the Chriſt, he was caſt out of the Synogogue; their Doctrine alſo depraved, for they made the fifth Commandement of no effect, a man might neglect his Parents by giving to the Temple; they forbad murther and adultery in the act, but allowed them in the heart; their Sacrifices alſo corrupted, offering the blinde and lame, which were not onely forbidden, but hatefull to God, in a word: the ſame people that the Lord cals his peculiar and choſen ones, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth alſo a ſtiffe-necked, unwiſe, and rebellious people, a ſinfull Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet all having right to the externall Covenant, and all joyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the externall worſhip, ordinances and ſervice of God; yet the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155268:5"/> ſcandalous infected not the better part, though they had fellowſhip in externall communion, therefore from hence we ſee a Church may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly corrupt, and yet be a true Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> was corrupt in Doctrine and Diſcipline.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In Doctrine, ſome of them erred in fundamentals,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.12. 1 Cor 7.16 2 Cor. 12.20, 21.</note> denying the Reſurrection of the dead.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They held the Doctrine of ſingle life, yea <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There were amongſt them fornicators, uncleane, and contentious perſons.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Divers prophane perſons came to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, ſome comming hungry, ſome drunke, and many of hereticall and ſchiſmaticall ſpirits and opinions, which are more hurtfull in the Church of God then prophane men, by reaſon one is an evill that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man knowes, the other being an errour to ſeduce the judgement, is more hurtfull and dangerous.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Corrupt in Diſcipline.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Their Diſcipline was not put in practiſe, for there was fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among them, not onely unpuniſhed, but unſorrowed for.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe Schiſmes and Hereſies continued in the Church, and no courſe taken for the caſting them out.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Conſider what the Churches of</hi> Aſia <hi>were.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Epheſus</hi> had loſt her firſt love.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In <hi>Smyrna</hi> divers profeſſed themſelves to be Jewes,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.4. Rev. 2 9. Rev. 2.14.15. Rev. 2. v. 19.20.</note> and were even of the Synagogue of Satan.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In <hi>Pergamus</hi> there were divers that held the Doctrine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> teaching to eate things ſacrificed to Idols, and to commit fornication, and divers that held the Doctrine of the <hi>Nicolaitanes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The Church of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> though the Lord commends her for her charity, faith, patience, as the other Churches, yet ſhee alſo ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Jezabel</hi> to ſeduce people to fornication and idolatry.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> had onely a name that ſhee lived, and was dead,<note place="margin">Rev. 3.1.4.</note> there were but a few names in <hi>Sardis</hi> that had not defiled their garments by ſpirituall fornication.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Philadelphia</hi> alſo had ſome that profeſſed themſelves Jewes,<note place="margin">Rev. 3.8.9.</note> yet were of the Synagogue of Satan, ſo ſome render it, however ſhe had but a little ſtrength.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Laodicea</hi> a remarkable Church for lukewarmneſſe, ſelfe conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yet poore, miſerable, blind, and naked.</p>
               <p>4. <hi>The Church of</hi> Galatia <hi>corrupt alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. They were even bewitched with the Doctrine of workes,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.12.7.</note> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155268:6"/> ſalvation had beene by keeping the Law, a fundamentall errour, for then Chriſt died in vaine.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They turned againe to weake and beggerly rudiments, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving dayes, moneths, times, and yeares, in ſo much that for their ſuperſtition <hi>Paul</hi> was afeard of them,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.10.11.</note> that though they profeſſed Chriſt, yet his labour was in vaine beſtowed upon them: yet all this while none of theſe evils in any of theſe Churches made a nullity of the Church, but they were called and accounted by the Lord Chriſt, and by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, true Churches of Chriſt, and that upon theſe three grounds before delivered in the propoſition at firſt laid downe concerning the markes of a viſible Church: for I ſpeake not now of the markes of an inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church, as theſe following, and ſuch like;
<list>
                     <item>1. To be borne of God.</item>
                     <item>2. To be knowne of God.</item>
                     <item>3. To have the Spirit of God.</item>
                     <item>4. To be joyned to Chriſt by faith: but of the markes of a true viſible Church, which are theſe three eſpecially and eſſentially;
<list>
                           <item>1. The preaching of the word of Chriſt.</item>
                           <item>2. Adminiſtration of the Sacraments.</item>
                           <item>3. Viſible profeſſion to both.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And it will appeare thus.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Acts 13.26.</note>1. If God would make a people to become his people or Church, he ſends his word, the Doctrine of ſalvation to them: Go, ſaith the Lord Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> teach all Nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, &amp;c. teaching them to obſerve all that I have commanded you; and loe, I am with you alwayes unto the end of the world, Amen: hence is that our Saviour ſpeakes concerning the Jewes,<note place="margin">John 4.22.</note> Salvation is of the Jewes, that is,<note place="margin">Acts 13.26.</note> the Word and Doctrine of ſalvation is with them, the Word and Doctrine of ſalvation is ſent to this purpoſe, that men may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,<note place="margin">Acts 18.10.</note> and for the ſake of beleevers, <hi>Paul</hi> alſo is ſaid to preach the Word at <hi>Corinth,</hi> becauſe the Lord had much people there to convert to him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Lord addes Seales of his Covenant to ſuch a people, as Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme and the Sacrament of the Lords Supper; for as Circumciſion was a ſigne of the Covenant betweene God and the Jewes under the Law,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.1.</note> ſo is Baptiſme to Chriſtians under the Goſpel: therefore our Lord Chriſt ſaith to his Diſciples, <hi>Goe, teach and baptize, &amp;c.</hi> And for the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment and ſtrengthening his people in his wayes, in their graces, the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">Acts 2.47. Ch. 4.5.</note>3. The viſible profeſſion of obedience to the Word of God and the Ordinances of God is the maine marke of a member of a viſible
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155268:6"/> Church, <hi>And the Lord added to the Church ſuch as ſhould be ſaved,</hi> that is, all that were ſaved made profeſſion of obedience to the Doctrine of Chriſt, and came into an externall Covenant with beleevers; not that all were ſaved, that were added to the Church, but the Lord brought them into the way of ſalvation by making them members of the Church: for though none were excluded that would profeſſe Chriſt, and ſuch as were ſaved were added to the Church, yet all that were added doubtleſſe to the viſible Church were not ſaved, for there was never ſuch a Church upon the face of the earth that had not unſound members: true, if we take it to be meant of the inviſible Church, then none are added but ſuch as are ſaved, but very hypocrites profeſſing the faith of Chriſt are members of the viſible Church: the Eunuch before he was baptized and admitted into the Church-fellowſhip made profeſſion of his faith: ſo that both godly and hypocrites muſt make profeſſion if they will be members of the viſible Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Doth there not actuall and inward obedience belong to a true Church as well as outward profeſſion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, to make men true members of the inviſible Church, but outward profeſſion is the viſible marke of a member of a viſible Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> If profeſſion ſerve the turne, then a true Church may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of hypocrites.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> No, it is impoſſible, for the Lord never ſends his word to any people but where he hath his owne number to call in, therefore <hi>Paul</hi> preached at <hi>Corinth</hi> becauſe the Lord had much people there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But many wicked men who are accounted members of the Church of England doe not make profeſſion of obedience to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, therefore they cannot be of the Church, neither can it be a true Church that countenances members that doe not ſo much as profeſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Although there be ſuch among our Aſſemblies, yet they are members, though unſound: for,</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are borne of Chriſtian parents, men profeſſing faith in Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are baptized into the Chriſtian faith, and ſo admitted and received as viſible members of the Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The moſt prophane of them, eſpecially ſuch as come to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of hearing and receiving the Sacraments, doe verbally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Chriſt though their converſation deny him, ſo that however God hath not given them grace to walke according to their profeſſion, yet they doe verbally confeſſe obedience to Chriſt and faith in his name,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155268:7"/> they acknowledge no other way of ſalvation, but by Chriſt, nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip no other God; all the outſide ſervice they doe is to the true God, though it be in a way of their owne periſhing; there were many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ones in the Church of the Jewes, and alſo in <hi>Corinth,</hi> yet true Churches, and theſe moſt of them in their beſt tempers and coole bloud will ſpeake well of the wayes of God, though in heart they hate the children of God under the notion of hypocrites, while they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are guilty in the higheſt degree of hypocriſie by their thruſting themſelves into the Aſſemblies of Gods people, claime intereſt in the Ordinances of God, nay in the Lord Chriſt, taking the name of God into their mouthes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.16.</note> yet hate to be reformed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Though there be many ſuch prophane wretches that thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Aſſemblies, yet the Lord hath his number of choſen ones that both profeſſe and practiſe obedience to the Goſpel, for whoſe ſake the Ordinances are continued, and the preſence of God in them, ſo that the uneven walking of wicked men doth neither take away the benefit of the Ordinances from the godly, nor give a nullity to the Church.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This alſo is that that will leave them one day without excuſe, that they ſinned in a Land of uprightneſſe, in the middeſt of ſo much light, and of enjoyment of ſo much means, and alſo aggravate their ſin, that they have preſumptuouſly laid claime to the Ordinances of God, and have beene negligent and careleſſe to walke ſutable, hereby they in the Sacrament eate and drinke to their owne damnation, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come guilty of the body and bloud of the Lord Chriſt in trampling his ſacred bloud under their feete, and crucifying to themſelves the Lord of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> The Church of the Jewes was a true Church, and ſo the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and the reſt named, they were a people in Covenant with God, rightly conſtituted, and there was never a nationall Church ſince the Jewes were rejected.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">
                     <note place="margin">Mr <hi>Bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rounds o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Sep <hi>pag.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Religion ever ſince the fal is all one in ſubſtance, thogh different in the diſpenſation, and the Church one and the ſame, though diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in its manner of government and meaſure of its gifts fitted to the ſeverall ages thereof; the myſteries are varied according to the times, but the faith whereby we live is the ſame in all ages, and as God is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, ſo is the Covenant unchangeable, that excepted which was peculiar to the manner of diſpenſation: the confederates and members of the Church one and the ſame by Gods approbation, and ſo the common nature and eſſence of all true Churches and eſſentiall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155268:7"/> conſtitution from the beginning to the end of the world. In all ages of the Church the members thereof ought to be holy and Saints, or they ſhall not be approved by God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.5.16.</note> they are Saints who have made a Covenant with God by way of Sacrifice: the wicked have nothing to doe with the Covenant, the end of the calling of the Church is holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the glory of God at all times, and is true in all ages.<note place="margin">Gen 4.26. Luke 20.26 Mat. 5.16. 1 Pet. 2.12. Acts 2.47.</note> And they which are unanſwerable to this end, or cleane contrary affected, they are not called into Covenant or communion with God: if in one age of a Church the Scripture aſcribe not holineſſe to a people for ſome few ſake, if the reſt be unholy and prophane, it aſcribes it not to them in any age.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">If in one ſtate of the Church uncleane perſons doe pollute,<note place="margin">Lev. 14.46, 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Hag. 2.12.13, 14. 1 Cor. 5 6, 7</note> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallow cleane perſons and things, as a little Leaven leaveneth the whole lumpe, this muſt hold true in every age in its proportion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">And therefore if ignorant, unwiſe, impenitent, uncircumciſed in hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and life, rebellious and ſtiffenecked in courſe and converſation, might be in externall Covenant with God, and (in that reſpect) a ſeparate and holy choſen people with whom the people of God might hold externall communion in the Ordinances of worſhip, then it is lawfull for Chriſtians to partake in the Ordinances of Gods worſhip, though ſcandalous livers be admitted, with whom in partaking we have onely externall communion: for if the ſcandalous were in Covenant in the Jewiſh Church, they may be ſo now; if communion with the wicked defile now, it defiled then;<note place="margin">Lev. 19.17.</note> if the godly might communicate then, becauſe they could not caſt them out, even ſo may they now; if the faithfull be bound now to reprove their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent brother, and not ſuffer ſinne to reſt upon him, the ſame duty concerned them in former times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">If the Sacraments be now available and of uſe according to Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and promiſe which God hath made to the faithfull and their ſeede, and no otherwiſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.7.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.4.</note> as indeed the Sacraments are all one in the common nature, ſo are they in their uſe onely available to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Covenant at all times. If it be contrary to the maine ends for which the Lord calleth and gathereth a Church, and preſerveth it upon the earth, that wicked and ungodly ſhould be received into Covenant, or permitted to continue in the externall ſociety of the faithfull,<note place="margin">Jer. 5.31. Jer. 9.2.3. Eſa 57.3. &amp; 1.4.</note> it was unlawfull in the Jewiſh Church as well as now in Chriſtian Churches. And therefore if the Church of the Jewes, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all that hath beene ſaid, were the true Church of God when it was corrupt in doctrine, manners, officers, ordinances of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155268:8"/> when the teachers were dumb Dogges,<note place="margin">Jer. 11.14. Eſa. 50.1. Jer. 3.11.2.13.11.</note> blinde guides, the Prophets propheſied lies, the Prieſts received gifts, and the people re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, adulterous, oppreſſours, an aſſembly of rebels, when the Prieſthood was bought and ſold, the Temple defiled, the Law cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with falſe gloſſes, and made voyde with ſinfull Traditions, when errour, hereſie, idolatry, oppreſſion, ſtubbornneſſe, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſinne was riſe among them. If for all this they continued the Lords viſible flocke, and the Lord owned them for his people, and the Prophets and faithfull held externall communion with them in the Ordinances of God, then the Covenant of God is not diſanulled with his people, nor the Church unchurched, though ignorant &amp; profane perſons are tolerated in the Aſſembly, nor the godly defiled, becauſe ſcandalous perſons are ſuffered to communicate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, I would faine know what may be ſaid of the Church of the Jewes in defence of it under the Law, that may not in a more ample and large ſenſe be ſpoken in juſtification of the Chriſtian Aſſemblies under the Goſpel. Firſt, for the Covenant made betweene God and them, chuſing them from other nations, to place his name among them, and making Covenant with them to be their God, and they his people; all was upon condition of faith and obedience, and this Covenant was made with them onely: but the Covenant under the Goſpel betweene God and his people is of a farre larger extent, reaching to all Nations, neither is his preſence limited to any one particular place or people as then it was;<note place="margin">Eſa. 55.1.2, 3, 4, 5.7. Joel 2.32. John 4.20, 21, 22, 23, 24.</note> nor his worſhip conſiſts of ſo many burdenſome Rites and Ceremonies, and legall performances; the diſpenſation of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants, and of the worſhip of God differ, but the condition is all one, made and built upon faith and obedience, as then it was; though they by faith ſaw the Lord Chriſt yet to come in types, figures and ſhadowes, we behold him in his word by faith already come, having finiſhed the worke of our redemption, and now abides in the Heavens to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for his people.</p>
               <p>God cals people now to him by the Word and by the Spirit, inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and outwardly, not by extraordinary revelations and apparitions, dreams and viſions as formerly, but by means of grace appointed &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained both for converting and building up to and in Jeſus Chriſt; they had the Temple, their Sacrifices, their Sacraments, the ſame God and the ſame Chriſt that we have, ſo we have our Temple, our Altar, our high Prieſt,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.1, 2, 3, 4. Mat. 28 19. Mat. 18.20.</note> our Sacrifices, our Sacraments, all in a more ſubſtantiall and ſpirituall manner; they had the Law, we the Goſpel; they the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Gods preſence, ſo we; they the promiſe of life and ſalvation by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155268:8"/> Chriſt, ſo we upon condition of faith and repentance:<note place="margin">Acts 19.18. Acts 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7. Marke 16.16. John 3.15.</note> they ſerved God under the Law, we under Grace. If God call a whole Nation to a viſible and externall Covenant with him by the preaching of the Word, the giving them the Ordinances of life and ſalvation, by giving them hearts to make profeſſion of obedience thereto, as in <hi>England</hi> the Lord hath done, I know nothing againſt it, but that <hi>England</hi> may be as true a Nationall Church as the Church of the Jewes was, and as lawfully called and conſtituted, though very corrupt in Diſciplin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d Doctrine, and members alſo: the Word may be preached to Heath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns and Infidels for converſion, as <hi>Paul</hi> did to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> and to the blaſphemous Jewes, and yet had no externall communion with them as members of the ſame body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Word may be preached to them that are without, for their converſion to the faith, to them that are within the Church by Baptiſme and externall profeſſion for their ſound converſion unto God from particular ſinnes and building forward in grace and godlineſſe: there is no communion with Heathens nor infidels, becauſe they are not of the Chriſtian ſociety, but ſcandalous perſons received in by Baptiſme, and not caſt out by publike cenſure, the Word is preached to them as members, and not as unto bare hearers; and they are admitted to the prayers of the Congregation as well as hearing of the Word, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing members of the externall Covenant; to uſe one Ordinance and not another, is to make a Schiſme in the Church, and as the preaching of the Word, not the bare tender of the Word, but the giving of it to dwell and abide with a people, is a note of a true Church, ſo is the hearing of the Word an act of communion with the Church: And if the preſence of wicked men at the Sacrament did defile the Ordinance to the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſo their preſence in hearing the Word would have the ſame effect to defile the Word alſo to the faithfull; but the preſence of the wicked defile not the ordinance to the worthy beleeving Communicant, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Word to the prepared and ſincere hearer, therefore it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to participate in mixt Aſſemblies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> If this be all that declares a Church to be a true Church, preaching of the Word, adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and viſible profeſſion thereunto of obedience, then the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may be a true Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> the Word of God is not truly taught, the Ordinances and Sacraments of the Lord Chriſt are not diſpenſed, therefore there can be no viſible profeſſion of obedience to them, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be a true Church.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:155268:9"/>
               <p>For conſider, it is not the preaching of ſome one truth or other, that is a marke of a true Church, when fundamentall points upon which ſalvation or damnation dependeth, are erroniouſly maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and that by the whole Church, as it is this day in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> that cannot poſſibly be a true Church of Jeſus Chriſt that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines univerſally fundamentall errors quite overthrowing the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt, you may call ſuch a Church, if you will, yea a true Church, but let it be a true Church of Antichriſt: For conſider,</p>
               <p n="1">1. They permit not the word of God, the Doctrine of ſalvation, but in an unknowne tongue,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. the whole chap.</note> that people cannot underſtand, quite contrary to the rule of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. They will not ſuffer private men, Lay men, ſo much as to reade the Scriptures, which is abſolutely againſt the command of Chriſt, and the ſalvation of mankind; the Lord Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Search the Scriptures, for they teſtifie of me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 5.39. Acts 17.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and in them yee thinke to have eternall life;</hi> and ſee the men of <hi>Berea</hi> commended by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> for that the Pope prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits upon paine of Inquiſition.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They preach and preſſe their owne tenets, the Popes Decrees, and their owne Traditions, before the commands of God, placing more infallibility and confidence in the Pope, a ſinfull mortall man, then in the Scriptures themſelves, which is the word of truth.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They are corrupt in ſuch fundamentals both in Doctrine and Diſcipline that cannot ſtand with a true Church of Chriſt:<note place="margin">2 Cor 5.14. Eph. 2.1. Luk. 17.10 Mat. 15.30 Hoſea 4.6. 2 Tim. 3.15 Mat. 9.3.4, 5, 6. Eſa. 42.1. Mat. 24.22.24. Luke 18.7. Rom. 9.11.11.15. Heb. 7.25. 1. Tim. 2.5. Heb. 12.24. Heb. 24. Mark 5.36. Rom. 3.25.27.</note> yea, very contradictions to the Word of God and to the eſſence of Chriſt as the all-ſufficient Saviour of all that beleeve, maintaining the Doctrine of Freewill, of merits, of inherent righteouſneſſe, maintaining alſo law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ignorance, nay commending it for the Mother of Devotion, which the Lord himſelfe ſaith, is the cauſe of periſhing; they hold alſo the Scripture is not ſufficient to ſalvation, but the Popes Canons muſt be added; they alſo hold and maintaine confeſſion of ſinnes to Prieſts.</p>
               <p>That the Pope and Popiſh Prieſts have power to forgive ſinnes, they can ſell pardons for money.</p>
               <p>They deny the Doctrine of Election and Predeſtination which the Word of God ſo fully holds out.</p>
               <p>They maintaine prayer for the dead, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.22.27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.8, 9.</p>
               <p>They make more Interceſſors and Mediators beſides Chriſt, who is and ought to be the onely Mediatour of our peace.</p>
               <p>They overthrow the Doctrine of Gods free Grace, and of juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by faith in Chriſt, by the workes of ſuper-erogation, merit, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:155268:9"/>
               <p>They worſhip Saints and Angels contrary to the Word and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, ordain ſeven Sacraments, five more then Chriſt ordained.<note place="margin">Eſa. 42.8. Col. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Rev. 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Acts 10.25, 26. Judg. 13 15 16. Mat. 4 10. Luk. 22.15 16, 17, 18, 19, 20. John 6.33.</note>
               </p>
               <p>They alſo turne the Sacrament of the body and bloud of Chriſt to an Idoll Maſſe, and maintaine that groſſe and palpable errour of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, which is quite againſt a cloud of witneſſes, <hi>John</hi> 6.53.54, 55, 56, 57, 58. <hi>John</hi> 6.63. <hi>John</hi> 16.7. the 17.10, 11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. <hi>John</hi> 6.47, 48, 50. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.23. and 26.11. <hi>Marke</hi> 16.19. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.2, 3. <hi>John.</hi> 16.28. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.1. and 10.12. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe and other fundamentall errours, as the palpable Idolatry, &amp;c. many other of leſſe concernement, as their Feaſt dayes, Faſt dayes, Doctrine of ſingle life to the Clergie, Diſpenſations to ſinne, &amp;c. that if ever there were a true Church (if I may ſo call it) of Antichriſt, it is the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> therefore I conclude that that Church which generally maintains fundamentall errours againſt the very being of the Word, the command of God, the eſſence of Chriſt, cannot be a true Church of Chriſt. But of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> this and more may be be truly affirmed: therefore the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> There are other markes of a true Church, as a lawfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery and true Diſcipline.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, both theſe are neceſſary in a Church, and we alſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a lawful Miniſtery where the Word is truly taught: and as for a true Diſcipline it is neceſſary to the well-being of a Church not eſſential to the being of a Church, the Church is not ſo well as it ought to be, that is defective this way, but yet there may be great corruptions in Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery and Diſcipline, and yet the Church be a true Church of God; as a man though he have ſome infirmity or imbecillity in his body, in ſome one or more members, though he be not ſo perfect a man as he would be or ſhould be, yet he may be, and is a reall man, as in caſe of the Palſie, and the like debility. This we know, that no true Church can be perfect in this life, either in the internall or externall frame thereof;<note place="margin">As all true Churches from the beginning have done.</note> for if not any one man, much leſſe a whole Congregation: and if the Lord be pleaſed to account the Church to be his, when it failes in the internals of the worſhip and ſervice of God, ſurely we have no reaſon to thinke ſo raſhly that he will decline and diſclaim it for outward defects where the fundamentals are preſerved and kept.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> The ſtanding and calling of our Miniſters as they ſtand by Biſhops, is Antichriſtian, and therefore they are not lawfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It would be ſomething difficult I thinke for thoſe that are of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155268:10"/> that opinion to prove either their propoſition or concluſion to be truth, but in anſwer hereof I ſay thus much.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4 15 Gal. 1.9. Luke 9.49.</note>1. If they preach the Lord Chriſt, and life and ſalvation by faith in his name.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If they ſhow forth the power of godlineſſe in their converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1.15.18.</note>3. If they be furniſhed with miniſteriall qualifications. Let their calling, ſtanding, and preaching, be allowed by Biſhops or not, they are no whit the more unlawfull in their ſtanding or practiſe:<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k. 9.38 39, 40. Num. 11.28 29.</note> ſo <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Meldad</hi> they propheſie, and <hi>Moſes</hi> allowes them; and deſires all Gods people were Prophets: <hi>viz.</hi> that they might be able to deliver the minde of God to the people: and truly we ſhould not envie, though there were a greater number furniſhed with miniſteriall gifts, whether allowed by Biſhops or not.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As Biſhops are Miniſters, they are lawfully called, and ſo may have a vote I conceive, though with ſubjection, in electing and ordaining preaching Miniſters as they are (or ought to be) men able to judge of mens learnings, parts, and qualifications, for the Miniſtery; for the ſpirits of the Prophets,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.32</note> are ſubject to the Prophets: as for that exorbitant power which they pretend they received from the King as Supreame Magiſtrate, or their uſurped authority exerciſed over the lives, liberties, eſtates, and conſciences of men; their great intermeddling with ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and temporall affaires and juriſdiction: this, though it be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, yet this makes not their callings to the Miniſtery unlawfull, or them uncapable of electing or ordination, no more then the abuſe of any calling makes the calling unlawfull, though men by abuſe may make themſelves unfit and uncapable of their lawfull callings. We muſt therefore condemne them in what they have done that is unlawfull and unjuſt; but the appointing Miniſters to preach the Word of God is a lawfull action, and not derogating from their function as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: and indeed we ſhould have had little or no cauſe to complaine of them for this, had they beene faithfull in the truſt repoſed in them, and appointed ſuch over and in the Church as were godly, learned, and painfull, and conſcionable in their places, ſuch who were called by God as well as approved of by them: <hi>Examp.</hi> If there were an order from Biſhops that none might pray in his family without order from them, would this order from them make our praying in our families unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full? no ſurely, neither doth their giving orders to Miniſters make their Miniſtery unlawfull, as it is lawfull to pray and preach without them, ſo is it with their conſent.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:155268:10"/>3. Know the principall call of a Miniſter is from God, for if men be rightly qualified and gifted for the Miniſtery, that they are inabled from God to deliver his minde out of his Word to his people, and preach ſound Doctrine approved of by the Scriptures, and the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full who are inabled by the Spirit of God to try the ſpirits whether they be of God, yea or no;<note place="margin">1 John 4.1.</note> this makes men lawfull Miniſters of the Word of God, whether approved by the Biſhops or diſallowed by them: and indeed this is that that Gods people ſhould eſpecially looke after, and leſſe trouble and puzle themſelves about their ſtanding or not ſtanding by Biſhops; I know if I ſhould aske ſuch men as account ſuch Miniſters Antichriſtian, and their callings unlawfull; whether the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops diſallowing or diſapproving of one rightly qualified for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery would make him uncapable and unlawfull to preach; they would anſwer as I doe my ſelfe, Certainely no: then I conclude that as their diſapproving of a man makes him not unlawfull, if he be quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, much leſſe their allowing or approving of him; for God is the great caller and ſender, and if he ſend men to preach, or call men,<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 9.38.39.</note> who ſhall contradict it? our duty therefore is to pray the Lord of the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt to ſend painfull labourers into his Vineyard.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Our Biſhops have placed over us prophane, idle, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, not fit to take charge of the flocke of Chriſt, yea and many as ignorant as prophane.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> For ſuch as are ignorant and unable and idle, theſe are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unfit, and this is the great ſinne of them that were in authority in the Church to ſuffer it: as for ſcandalous and prophane livers, they alſo are ſinfully thruſt upon the Church, but if they preach well and truly, take paines in the Miniſtery, the viciouſneſſe of their lives make them not altogether unlawfull in their ſtandings, though they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable by reaſon of that prejudice which we receive againſt their practiſe, though their Doctrine be true, and this is of our ſelves, and ariſes of our corrupt hearts to decline and turne our backs upon whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome truths, though delivered by ſinfull men:<note place="margin">Mat. 15 5. Mat. 16 6. &amp; 26.65. Iſay. 57.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Ezek. 34 3.</note> the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, as before, were ignorant, unlearned, blinde guides, hypocrites, ambitious, covetous, and the Prieſts of old under the Law were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and unholy, yet the Doctrine of truth was to be received from them; for Gods people ſhould be like Bees ſucking ſweetneſſe out of Thiſtles, while wicked men like the Adder gather poyſon out of flowers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> The Prieſts under the Law, the Scribes and Phariſees were rightly called, therefore they ought to heare them, but ours are not.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:155268:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> What <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelfe, that he was not an Apoſtle by man nor of man, but by Jeſus Chriſt, and God the Father, that is true of all the Apoſtles, not onely becauſe they were to preach Chriſt, but received Commiſſion from him, and are therefore called the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of Jeſus Chriſt, (not in after times) for then we muſt prove whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the Apoſtles delivered the power of government to the community of the faithfull as they received it from Chriſt, for which there is no Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: the Miniſters and guides of the Church are immediately of Jeſus Chriſt, from whom they derive their power and receive their charge, in whoſe name they muſt execute their office,<note place="margin">Acts 20.28.</note> and to whom they muſt give an account whoſe Miniſters they are; Take heed to your ſelves and to the whole flocke over which the holy Ghoſt hath made you O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeers: the Presbyters at <hi>Epheſus</hi> we ſee were appointed Overſeers by the holy Ghoſt, that they might governe the Church of God, they were choſen and ordained of men, and ſo by immediaty of perſon, not from God as were the Apoſtles, &amp;c. but their gifts, off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce, and authority was immediately of God: in conferring thoſe offices God uſeth the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of men, but the office and authority is from God alone: (when Chriſt aſcended on high, he gave gifts to men, ſome to be Apoſtles, ſome Prophets,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.8.11 1 Cor. 12.8</note> ſome Evangeliſts, ſome Paſtors, ſome Teachers) ſo that the Paſtorſhip and office of teaching and their gifts are as imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from Chriſt as the Apoſtleſhip was, and though every Paſtor is not immediately called, yet the office and order is from Chriſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, and not from men, and ſo is their authority and juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; and ſo our Miniſters that are gifted from God and by God, are as lawfull Teachers,<note place="margin">Mat. 24 41 Tit. 1.7. Mat. 9.38. 1 Cor. 12 5. Phil. 1.1. Col. 1.24. 2 Cor. 6.4. Rom. 1.1. 2 Cor. 4 5. 1 Cor. 4.1.5. Argum. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ncerning our M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs one to apply to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe that ſcandall them.</note> and have as much warrant from God as the Apoſtles had in their time, whether approved by men or not, the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt is the Lords, and to him it belongs to ſend labourers: now there be differences of Miniſters, but the ſame Lord, the Miniſters of the Word are not the Ambaſſadours of men but of Chriſt, as having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their office, power, and gifts from him, and not of the Church; they may be called the Miniſters of the Church as the Lords Miniſters and ſervants, or the Church is Miniſters or ſervants are taken indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, becauſe, though the Lord ſend them, and gift them, yet it is for the ſake of the Church, and they ought rather to be called the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt then of the Church, for all power Spirituall and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall is of God.</p>
               <p>And as for thoſe that account our Miniſters Antichriſtian, though never ſo godly in their lives, or ſound in Doctrine, by reaſon of their ſtanding by Biſhops, I deſire them to conſider theſe ſixe Arguments fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155268:11"/> five of which may be applied truly to many of our Miniſters, who the thus brand with that odious term of Antichriſtian Miniſters.</p>
               <p n="1">1. No man that truly preaches Chriſt, and both in his life and Doctrine ſets himſelfe againſt Antichriſt, and his followers,<note place="margin">1 Cor 12 3 Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 12.25, 26. Mat. 7.16. 1 Cor. 2.11 1 Cor 3.11 2 Cor. 4.5. 1 Cor 10.31. 1 Theſ. 2 6 Mark 9 38 39. 1 Cor. 2.4.</note> can be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Antichriſtian.</p>
               <p n="2">2. No man that expreſſes the power of godlineſſe in his life and converſation, can be accounted Antichriſtian.</p>
               <p n="3">3. No man that makes Jeſus Chriſt and the glory of God the maine end of his preaching, can be Antichriſtian.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He that labours both by Doctrine and practiſe, or by either of them, to convert men to Jeſus Chriſt, and to diſſwade men from the wayes of Antichriſt, this man cannot be antichriſtian.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He that to his power ſhowes his diſlike of corruptions, both of Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of God, and indeavours for reformation by earneſt prayer and ſuch other meanes as are in the bounds of his place and calling, and mournes for the continuance of them in the Church, this man cannot be guilty of the corruptions in the Church, much leſſe Antichriſtian.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To oppoſe Chriſt in his Miniſters or members,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.3 Gal. 1.8.</note> to ſcandall the wayes of God, the Miniſters and the Ordinances of God, the publike aſſemblies of his people; this I conceive is a high degree of Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſme and blaſphemy.</p>
               <p>And truly as I am confident that there is none of the firſt five aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but may well be applied to many hundreds of our Miniſters for their juſtification from that aſperſion of Antichriſtianiſme ſo maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly caſt upon them, ſo I ſpeak it with griefe of heart, I feare the laſt aſertion, which ſhowes plainely who are Antichriſtian, will of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fall upon the heads of all ſuch as with open and blacke mouthes ſcandall the wayes, Miniſters, Ordinances, publike Aſſemblies of the people of God in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> proceeding to a high degree of Antichriſtianiſme and blaſphemy: for this is that maine deceit of the Devill, to vilifie the Ordinances and adminiſtrations thereof in the Church by calling them idolatrous, and the people Idolaters, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian, or elſe he could never prevaile with men whoſe hearts would elſe reverence and reſpect them; and herein I conceive is that fulfilled of Satan, transforming himſelfe into an Angel of light; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could any man perſwade himſelfe it were lawfull to ſeparate from our publike Aſſemblies, were it not that he is perſwaded the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Officers, and Aſſemblies, are ſo in deed, which neither they nor the Devill himſelfe can ever be able to make appeare out of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155268:12"/> Word of God: Indeed no man, Miniſter, or other that beleeve in Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 John 1.1.</note> and deſire to walke with God in uprightneſſe, as many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in the Church of <hi>England</hi> doe, can be counted other then the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> and he that preaches any other Doctrine, we ought to hold him accurſed? Thus much concerning the lawfulneſſe of our Church Aſſemblies and Adminiſtrations: now to prove the lawfulnes of joyning with them in Ordinances.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> What ſhall we doe then that are to joyne in mixt Aſſemblies, that we ſin not herein?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Take heede of joyning with any corruption or knowne evill in the Church, ſhow your diſlike of it according to your power.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Exhort and admoniſh, or reprove as the circumſtance of thy cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, relation, and opportunity will give leave, thoſe that have no right to the Ordinances.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Mourne for the abominations and corruptions in the Church, and wraſtle earneſtly with godly prayers for reformation, but deſiſt not thy duty though Miniſters be corrupt, and many people prophane at the Sacrament, doe thou prepare thy owne heart and receive to thy comfort; for know thus much, there never yet was any v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ible Church of God upon earth that was without its corruptions in Doctrine, in manners, in officers, in members, as hath beene ſufficiently ſhowed concerning the Church of the Jewes, <hi>Corinth, Galatia,</hi> and the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia:</hi> yet I never read of any toleration to ſeparate from them, or that they ceaſed to be true Churches by reaſon of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Our Saviour Chriſt departed not from the publike Aſſemblies of the Jewes,<note place="margin">Luke 2.</note> for he was circumciſed and ſo admitted a member of the Aſſemblies.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Luke 2 22.</note>2. His Mother was purified, and he preſented, and an offering gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for him as for other children.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">Luke 2.40.</note>3. When he came to age he was content to heare them, he was found amongſt them in the Temple, where there was alſo prayer and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching every Sabbath day.<note place="margin">Acts 16.13.14.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. He obſerved their Feaſt of Paſſeover, and his Diſciples eate it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, as Divines give it forth from the 26. <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.3. and <hi>John</hi> 2.23. however he obſerved it as they did.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He was baptized among them publikely, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.13.15. <hi>Marke</hi> 1.9.</p>
               <p n="6">6. He allowed his Diſciples to doe as he had done, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.12. exhorting them to heare their Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> the Scribes and Phariſees,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155268:12"/> thogh they ſhould not follow their practiſe, becauſe they had the Word of God taught among them, though their lives were unanſwerable: ſo that he tolerates none to ſeparate, neither by his Doctrine or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; Salvation, ſaith he, is of the Jewes, <hi>John</hi> 4.24. that is, the Word of ſalvation is with them, or ſalvation is had among them by the meanes of grace with them: So alſo ſee <hi>Pauls</hi> example.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> was ſo exceedingly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt both in Doctrine and Diſcipline, as hath beene ſaid formerly, yet he gives no toleration to ſeparate, but rather ſhowes in ſuch caſes what Gods people ſhould doe, out of whoſe power it was, and is to reforme abuſes in the Church, <hi>viz.</hi> private Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Showes them their errour in admitting unworthy receivers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The danger of unworthy receiving, and how farre it extended to their owne deſtruction and condemnation, beſides thoſe temporall diſeaſes and ſickneſſes brought alſo upon ſuch diſorderly Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Showes them the right inſtitution of it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The cure and remedy of this malady that it might not be hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the whole Church, Let every man therefore examine himſelfe, looke to his owne heart, and ſo let him eate, &amp;c. not, Let any one ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; if that had beene the way, ſurely he would have ſaid, there is an inceſtuous perſon not caſt out, there are ſchiſmes, ſtrifes, and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, there are drunkards, &amp;c. in the Church, men of ſtrange opinions, come not among them, nor partake of the Sacrament with them, leſt you eate and drinke damnation to your ſoules: no, no ſuch matter, ſuch there are among you, ſaith he, but every one of you examine your owne ſoules, prove your ſelves, that you be not of the number of them: and ſo eate, and ſo drinke to your comfort, though the other eate and drinke damnation to themſelves. And further, ſtirres them up to the duty, 1. By ſhowing them what he delivered to them he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from Chriſt. 2. That it was their duty ſo to doe, for thereby they kept a a continuall remembrance of Chriſt, and ſhewed forth the death of the Lord till he come; one of the maine ends of the inſtitution of this Sacrament: See the example of Gods people in former ages.</p>
               <p>The ſin of <hi>Elies</hi> ſons was very great, as great as any Miniſters can be, and as publike, they were impudent, lying with women before the doore of the Tabernacle, they prophaned the Sacrifices, yet the people of God came accuſtomarily to <hi>Shilo,</hi> where they did adminiſter to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their duty, notwithſtanding the wickedneſſe of the Prieſts, as <hi>Elkanah</hi> and <hi>Hannah:</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the Church was wonderfully cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155268:13"/> both in Prieſt and people, yet the faithfull in it that mourned, not ſeparated,<note place="margin">Ezek. 9 4.</note> are taken ſpeciall notice of; ſo in our Saviours time he gives them no toleration to ſeparate from the Church of the Jewes, but to hear them &amp; joyn with them,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.12</note> and if any man can give me any exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of any member either under the Law, or in Chriſt, or the Apoſtles time, that did ſeparate from the publike Aſſemblies of Gods worſhip, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had any warrant ſo to doe out of the word of God, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the great corruptions that hath beene proved to be in Churches in all ages, then I ſhould thinke they ſpeake ſomething to the purpoſe; true indeed, for Jewes to ſeparate from Infidels and the Heathen Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Idolatrous practiſe, and ſo for Chriſtians under the Goſpel, ſo to doe, is juſtifiable, and both commanded by God, and expected to be done, but for one Jew to ſeparate from the publike Aſſemblies of Gods worſhip from other Jewes, or one Chriſtian from the publike Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and worſhip of God from the reſt, this I never read of.</p>
               <p>But to ſpeake more fully to this purpoſe, I will, 1. anſwer thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments given in to maintaine a ſeparation from our publike Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies as they were given unto me, in the controverting of this point.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I will ſhow the lawfulneſſe of joyning in our mixt Aſſemblies.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The unlawfulneſſe to ſeparate.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Give ſatisfaction in ſome meaſure to thoſe places of Scripture that are brought in defence of that opinion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Give caution to keepe off aſperſion or prejudice that may be caſt upon me or any of my judgement in this point.</p>
               <p>Their firſt Argument is this:</p>
               <p>They that ſee the Lord Chriſt crucified are guilty of the body and bloud of Chriſt: but Gods people at the Sacrament ſee the Lord Chriſt crucified by wicked men: therefore they are guilty of the body and bloud of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Argument is falſe in every part of it. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Men may ſee the Lord Chriſt crucified, and not be guilty of the body and bloud of Chriſt, for it is the very maine end and uſe of the Lords Supper to behold Chriſt crucified, and to ſhow the Lords death till he come in a ſpeciall manner.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If all that ſee Chriſt crucified ſhould be guilty of his death and of his body and bloud, then <hi>Mary</hi> the mother of Chriſt and his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and friends that ſaw him deſpightfully uſed by the Jewes when he was haled and nailed to the Croſſe, who were heartily gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eved at it, and would if they could, have prevented it, were guilty o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the body and bloud of Chriſt; and all that ſaw <hi>Judas</hi> betray Chriſt, by the ſame
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:155268:13"/> reaſon were guilty of betraying him alſo, even the Diſciples them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Know, no godly man can be guilty of the body and bloud of Chriſt, as every ungodly man is; for no man in the ſtate of grace and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, &amp;c. yet they hold that Gods people can be guilty ſeeing Chriſt crucified by wicked men at the Sacrament of the Lords Supper are guilty, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Their Argument ſhould therefore have runne thus, They that either crucifie Chriſt, or joyne with them that doe crucifie him, are guilty of the body and bloud of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But wicked men at the Sacrament of the Lords Supper doe crucifie Chriſt, and Gods people in comming to the Sacrament with them doe joyne with them: therefore they are both guilty of the body and bloud of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This Argument for the major and minor,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.27.29.</note> may be granted with ſome caution, but the aſſumption is falſe: for grant that wicked men in the Sacrament doe crucifie the Lord Chriſt, it is onely to themſelves, and they are themſelves guilty of the body and bloud of Chriſt: wee may grant alſo that thoſe that joyne with them doe alſo crucifie Chriſt, and ſo become guilty of, &amp;c. but with this exception or caution following.</p>
               <p>There is a twofold joyning with wicked men.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>And both theſe wayes.</head>
                  <item>1. With their perſons
<list>
                        <item>1. Voluntarily.</item>
                        <item>2. Accidentally, or Occaſionally.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. In their actions.
<list>
                        <item>1. Voluntarily.</item>
                        <item>2. Accidentally, or Occaſionally.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>A man may come in the company of a wicked man, and yet not joyne with him, if accidentally a man by reaſon of his buſineſſe in his generall or particular calling, or the like: nay, a man may voluntarily be in the company of a wicked man, being lawfully called to it, as in common and publike meetings, either concerning Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and yet not guilty of his evill actions; that which makes a man guilty of another mans actions, is approving them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to them, voluntary joyning in the action with them, not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry comming into their company and being with them accidentally or occaſionally: as for example, a wicked man and a godly man come to heare the Word, it is both their duties ſo to doe; if the wicked man ſhall purpoſely come to inſnare the Miniſter, to cut a Purſe, to doe ſome other miſchiefe; if the godly man have no ſuch end or intent, if he ſhow his diſlike of it, exhort him and reprove him for it, and uſe all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155268:14"/> lawfull wayes and meanes to reclaime him: How can he be guilty of joyning with him? ſo in the Sacrament it is the duty of the godly man to receive the Sacrament upon due preparation, if wicked men will thruſt themſelves in to that ſacred Ordinance without preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he that comes as he ought, ſhowing his diſlike of this abuſe, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring by ſeaſonable exhortation, or reproofe, or information, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the abuſe, and in caſe authority doe not reforme it, if he mourne for it, and pray againſt it, how can this man be ſaid to joyne with that wicked man? Nay, the one eates and drinkes the body and bloud of Chriſt to ſalvation, the other crucifies Chriſt afreſh to his owne dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: therefore I conclude that Argument thus; that which a man utterly diſlikes, condemnes, is humbled for, prayes againſt, labours to reforme to the utmoſt of his ability, cannot be accounted that mans guilt: but Gods people, &amp;c. doe utterly diſlike, &amp;c. the ſinfull approachings of wicked men to the Lords Table, mourne for it, pray againſt it: therefore, &amp;c. the ſinnes of another man muſt not make me decline my duty, but it is my duty to prepare, examine, and receive the Sacrament, therefore the ſinnes of wicked men comming to it, is no reaſon for me to decline or ſeparate from it, the principall part of the duty lies in ſelfe-examination,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.28.</note> not ſo much in examination of others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Gods people doe not doe their duty herein, true; peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they pray againſt it, and are humbled for it, but they doe not their beſt indeavour by reproofe, exhortation, and information, either to reclaime ſuch, or to have them caſt out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> So farre as they fall ſhort of their duty, herein they ſinne, but if they ſhould totally neglect this duty of exhorting, reproving, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt, mourning for, &amp;c. which it is impoſſible for any godly man to doe; yet this would not warrant them to ſeparate, for this were but the adding one ſinne to another.</p>
               <p>Againe, ſuppoſe the party offending be not capable of admonition, or will not reforme, then you will ſay we muſt tell it to the Church; now ſuppoſe the guides Temporall and Eccleſiaſticall, to whom the matter muſt be brought, be ſo corrupt, that they would countenance the offendor, and puniſh the complainant, eſtabliſh the diſorder rather then redreſſe it: What ſhall the innocent then doe? muſt he complaine to his undoing, or leave his ſtanding in the Church as unlawfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he cannot doe the duties which God calleth for at his hands? the Shepheards of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were many times blinde, ignorant, vitious, robbers, hirelings, vaine perſons; ſo the Scribes and Phariſees, if the Diſciples or the faithfull ſhould have ſought to them for Reformation
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:155268:14"/> of abuſes in the Church, what could have beene expected?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.10 2 Cor. 11.13. Gal. 1.6.</note> the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Paſtors we know built hay and ſtubble upon the foundation <hi>Paul</hi> had laid amongſt them, were falſe Apoſtles, deceitfull workers; in <hi>Galatia</hi> the Paſtors troubled the Church with corrupt Doctrine: in the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> all the Angels were reprehended, and ſo our Biſhops, Miniſters, and Magiſtrates were all ſo corrupted, that no man durſt complaine of abuſes in the Church, nay nor himſelfe with ſafety diſcharge his owne duty, what ſhould the faithfull doe? depart from the Ordinances of grace while God is pleaſed to dwell among them, or neglect the duty God hath called them to, and ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in other mens ſinnes? the Congregation it ſelfe divided or remiſſe the greateſt part the worſt, ſo that the beſt cannot be held among them, truth cannot take place, ſuch diviſion and diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> that the houſe of <hi>Cloe</hi> was conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to complaine to the Apoſtle, moſt of them ſo puffed up in the caſe of the inceſtuous perſon, that it had beene vaine for the better ſort to have ſought the caſting him out, had not the Apoſtle ſharply reproved them, their abuſive comming to the Lords Table was generall, ſo that the better ſort might grieve at it, but could not reforme it; in this caſe the faithfull cannot tell the Church, for that it is divided,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.11 1 Cor. 5.1.2</note> and as in our times the greateſt part holding the worſt ſide, depart they muſt not, for the Lord is in the Church and Ordinances, and they muſt not leave them till the Lord forſakes them; what remaines then, but that with mercifull affections they diſlike, reprove, and correct as much as in them lieth what they finde amiſſe, what they cannot amend, indure and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer patiently, and in loving ſort lament and bewaile till God doe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and amend it, or make way for their inlargement, and though ſome will ſay, but all this while they doe not their duty. I ſay rather the Lord requires not that particular duty at that time, becauſe they have no opportunity or meanes to doe it;<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Bal cap.</hi> 11. <hi>fol.</hi> 223.</note> thoſe that looke for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſatisfaction herein, I deſire them to reade Mr. <hi>Bals</hi> booke, a triall of the grounds tending to ſeparation.</p>
               <p>2. <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To have fellowſhip with them we are forbidden, to have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with all is ſinne, but godly men in the Sacrament have fellowſhip with prophane, which is forbidden; therefore they ſinne. This they labor to prove, <hi>Num.</hi> 15.30. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.3. both places improperly alleadged</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Though we ſhould grant the propoſition, that it is ſinne to have fellowſhip with thoſe we are forbidden, yet we deny that Gods people have fellowſhip with wicked men in the Sacrament, nor
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155268:15"/> with the workes if they diſlike and diſallow of their actions, labour with God and man for redreſſe ſo farre as they are able in the place God hath ſet them, what fellowſhip have they with them? as we ſaid before in point of joyning, ſo I ſay in point of fellowſhip, it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very occaſionall or accidentall comming in wicked mens company that gives me fellowſhip with them, or makes me guilty of their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Have no fellowſhip, ſaith the Apoſtle, with unfruitfull workes of darkneſſe, but rather reprove them, intimating ſtrongly, that he that reproves or diſlikes of the actions of others, cannot be ſaid to have fellowſhip with them, nay a man may have no fellowſhip with them, though he ſhould not reprove them, as appears by the word <hi>(ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther)</hi> reprove them; implying, if he did not conſent and ſin'd with them though he reprove them not, he had no fellowſhip with them: it is our duty to ſhow our diſlike of their abuſive comming to the Lords Table,<note place="margin">Gen. 4 4. Lev. 10.</note> not to ſeparate from the Ordinances: What fellowſhip had <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell</hi> with <hi>Cai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>?</hi> both ſacrificed together; or <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> with <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dab</hi> and <hi>Abibu?</hi> or what fellowſhip had <hi>Elkanah</hi> and <hi>Hannah</hi> with <hi>Elies</hi> wicked ſonnes,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.3.</note> who went up yearely to <hi>Shilo</hi> where they did miniſter? their ſinne was not charged upon them, becauſe they were in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany performing their duty: What fellowſhip had our Saviour Chriſt with the Jewes, Scribes, and Phariſees? What fellowſhip had the reſt of the Diſciples with <hi>Judas?</hi> they kept him company after they knew he was to betray the Lord Chriſt: or what fellowſhip had the beleeving <hi>Corinthians</hi> with the inceſtuous perſon before he was caſt out, and with thoſe other diſordered <hi>Corinthians</hi> that came with them to the Sacrament? truly they neither had fellowſhip with them nor their evill actions, neither was their ſinnes charged upon the faithfull and godly worthy communicants. If you ſay my preſence among them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves of their ſinne, by the ſame reaſon ye may ſay my preſence with them in hearing the Word approves of their ſinne, when as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is a voluntary preſence and a conſtrained preſence; indeed, if I lived as they doe in profaneneſſe, and followed their wicked practiſes, I ſhould then approve them, but my abominating them in my life, ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my diſlike of them, ſhowes plainely I approve them not, neither can their ſinne be any way charged upon me.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They that have power given them to doe that that makes for Gods glory and the Churches good, and doe not exerciſe it, they ſinne; but the Church in not exerciſing its power to caſt out offendors of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which would make much for Gods glory and the Churches bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:155268:15"/> doth ſinne: this they labour to prove in that 18. <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.18. which ſpeaketh of a particular offence betweene man and man, how we ſhould proceed in love and brotherly affection one with another: and if this were meant of abuſe in and about the Sacrament where they would have us after a ſecond admonition and witneſſe to tell the Church, I have anſwered it ſufficiently in the cloſe of the firſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: in caſe of particular injury, I ought before I come to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to labour for reconciliation, but if he will be cauſeleſly offended, I muſt not turne my back upon the Ordinances of God, and in caſe the Church doth reprove him, and he will not heare the Church let him be as a Publican or a profane perſon, have no unneceſſary familiarity with him, but his incorrigible Condition, muſt not cauſe me to decline my duty.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I anſwer, what power the Church hath is one thing, what particular members have is another; if the Church be remiſſe in exerciſe of Diſcipline, this gives me no warrant to ſeparate: for unleſſe the neglect of Diſcipline give a nullity to the Church, and take away the uſe and benefit of the Ordinances of God from me, it is no part of my duty to ſeparate, but pray God to reforme the abuſe, and make me a worthy receiver; for if it were ſo that the corruption in remiſſeneſſe of Diſcipline had given a nullity to the Church,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.5.</note> then the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> had ceaſed to be a Church when the inceſtuous perſon was not caſt out, and ever after ſo long as thoſe fornicators, dunkards, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and diſordered perſons were amongſt them: but we ſee by the text it was nothing ſo, it was their ſinne, they ſorrowed not, and not their ſinne, they ſeparated not themſelves, therefore the Apoſtle gives them admonition to examine themſelves, and ſo to come to the Table of the Lord.</p>
               <p>4. <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They that be Stewards and have rule given to walke by, ſinne in not walking by the rule; it is required of a Steward that he be found faithfull:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> but the Miniſters and officers in the Church have rule given to walke by, and if they doe not walke accordingly, they ſinne: now if they exerciſe not the Diſcipline of the Church, they walke not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to rule, and ſo are ſinfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though the Miniſters and other officers in the Church doe ſinne herein, what ground doth this give me to ſeparate? yet that place alleadged hath no relation at all to the Diſcipline of the Church, but that Miniſters of God ought to be faithfull in diſpenſing the ſecrets and truths of God, if they be faulty, this is not to the matter in hand,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:155268:16"/> unleſſe you would inferre, becauſe they ſinne in declining the duty, I muſt alſo ſinne in declining mine by ſeparating from the Ordinances of life and ſalvation; ſee the caſe of <hi>Elies</hi> ſons, &amp;c. <hi>Elkanah</hi> and <hi>Hannah</hi> might have ſaid, <hi>Elies</hi> ſons are wicked, and they deale vilely with the Ordinances of God, therefore we will not go up to <hi>Shilo</hi> to worſhip: a very unſound concluſion.</p>
               <p>5. <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> That that offends the weake, the ſtrong Chriſtian ought not to doe: but comming to the Sacrament with wicked men offends the weake Chriſtian: therefore the ſtrong Chriſtian ought not to doe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In caſes of indifferencie the weake muſt not be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended though the thing we doe in it ſelfe be lawfull, but we muſt take heed of complying with ſinfull weakneſſes, or neglect duties of ſo high concernement, as on which ſalvation and ſoule nouriſhment depend; though he be offended I ought rather to uſe meanes to reforme his judgement then to decline my duty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exam.</hi> If a man ſhould be offended for my obſerving the Lords day, for my praying in my family, for indeavouring to keepe the commands of God, muſt I neglect theſe weighty duties to humour his weakneſſe? nay rather I ſhall doe my duty to informe him what his duty is, both by my exhortation, admonition, reproofe, or practiſe.</p>
               <p>Beſides, though it be his weakeneſſe to be offended at ſuch duties of neceſſity to be performed, yet I ſhall ſinne againſt knowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, if I upon ſo ſlight grounds turne my back upon the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God.</p>
               <p>6. <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That that encourages wicked men in their ſinnes, a godly man ought not to doe: but comming with them to the Sacrament encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages them in their ſinnes: therefore a godly man ought rather to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">This is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the name of a beleeving &amp; worthy com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>municant.</note>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1. I do not encourage them in their ſinnes by my comming to the Sacrament, unleſſe I lived as they doe in the like or the ſame ſinnes, and came unworthily and unpreparedly to the Table of the Lord as they doe, then indeed I gave ill example and occaſion of incouragement; they ſee my life anſwerable to my profeſſion, but theirs clean contrary, and it is impoſſible for a godly man to countenance wicked men this way, for then he would ceaſe to be godly; if they come unprepared, and with impenitent and unbeleeving hearts, this is their ſinne, not mine.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How doe I incourage them by comming when I doe the beſt I can
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:155268:16"/> to dehort them from it, ſhow my diſlike of it, nay reprove them, and uſe all lawfull and neceſſary meanes to reclaime them or deterre them from it?</p>
               <p n="3">3. What evill effects depend upon the performance of my duty, I muſt not altogether ſo looke upon as to decline my duty, for as I muſt not doe the leaſt evill that the greateſt good may come upon it, ſo I muſt not neglect doing that which is good and enjoyned by God though ſome ſeeming evils enſue upon it.</p>
               <p>For then by the ſame reaſon I muſt leave off profeſſing Religion, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Sabbath, praying in my family, ſtanding for the cauſe of Chriſt, nay frequenting all publike and private duties and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, becauſe from hence wicked men take occaſion to ſcandall the waies of God, and reproach Gods people with nicknames, as Puritan, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt, Round-head, &amp;c. for the reaſon why wicked men hate Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is, becauſe they runne not with them to the ſame exceſſe of riot; and Gods people it is their part and duty to ſuffer for the name of Chriſt: the maine ground why <hi>Caine</hi> hated his brother <hi>Abell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.4. Luke 6.12.14.</note> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his workes were good, and his evill, for every one that doth evill hateth the light, therefore it is my part to looke what God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of me to performe,<note place="margin">John 3.20.</note> that I muſt have reſpect unto and leave the ſucceſſe and event to the Lord.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If my comming with them to the Sacrament barely conſidered, encourage wicked men in their ſinnes becauſe they come alſo, by the ſame reaſon my comming with them to heare the Word, doth alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them, and as much reaſon I have to turne my backe upon one Ordinance as another, becauſe of their frequenting them, for though it be lawfull and expedient that they ſhould heare the Word, being the meanes of converſion, and unlawfull for them to receive the Sacrament in the profaneneſſe, yet they not diſcerning the difference may take as much encouragement in their ſinnes by the godly hearing the Word with them, as receiving the Sacrament among them, and as much reaſon there is for one as the other, the premiſes conſidered.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As my prepared and worthy receiving can doe them no good that come unprepared and in their ſinnes, ſo their unprepared and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinfull preſumptious approaching the Ordinance can doe me no hurt, that is, cannot take the benefit of the Ordinance from me the cautions of diſlike of them formerly obſerved, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>7. <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that ſees a man murder himſelfe, and is preſent with him, is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his ſinne if he hinder him not, but godly men in the Sacrament
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:155268:17"/> ſee wicked men murder themſelves, and hinder them not, therefore they are guilty of their ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I referre the anſwer of this Argument to that firſt Argument of ſeeing wicked men crucifie the Lord Chriſt in the Sacrament, and the concluſion upon it, this Argument being of the ſame nature is there ſufficiently ſpoken to.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Argument.</p>
               <p>That that brings judgement upon the Church and people of God, Gods people ought to avoyd and ſhunne: but the comming with profane men to the Table of the Lord, brings judgement upon the Church and people of God: therefore they ought to avoyd and ſhun this evill, 1 <hi>Car.</hi> 11.30.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. It is not my comming preparedly and worthily that brings judgement upon the Church, but the diſorderly and profane comming of profane men.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The judgement that fell upon the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> of ſickneſſe and death, doubtleſſe was upon the profane and unworthy, not upon the guiltleſſe, for ſaith the Apoſtle, they eate and drinke Judgement to themſelves, for though the Apoſtle ſay, <hi>for this cauſe many of [you] are ſicke, and many ſleepe;</hi> he meaneth certainely many of your publike Aſſemblies which by their profaneneſſe have provoked God, and by reaſon they were members of their publike Aſſemblies, he ſaith many of [you] and not for that they were Saints that ſuffered: the diſorders, diviſions, drunkenneſſe and profaneneſſe of many of the Aſſemblies in comming to the Lords Table, was puniſhed, in ſome that belonged to the election of grace with temporall chaſtiſements, in ſome that were veſſels of wrath with death and eternall vengeance: and therefore not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding theſe abuſes in the Church he gives no toleration to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate, but laies downe what our duty is, even every man to be more watchfull over his own heart and life, and more diligent in the work of ſelf-examination, and ſo to eat and drink with comfort, and this is the onely remedy he preſcribes; he ſaith not, if ſuch and ſuch offendors be not caſt out, ſeparate your ſelves; nay he ſpeaks not at all, of caſting out any but the inceſtuous perſon: but if neither the other offenders nor the inceſtuous ſhould be caſt out, he I ſay ſaith not ſeparate, but be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, you in whoſe power it is not to caſt out, &amp;c. mourne for it at leaſt, rejoyce not in it, examine your owne hearts, prove your ſelves, and ſo eate of this bread and drinke of this cup: and gives them a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why they ſhould not depart the Aſſemblies, or decline their duty; <hi>For as often as yee eate this bread and drinke this cup, yee ſhow the Lords
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:155268:17"/> death till he come.</hi> So that I conclude with the Apoſtle, that ſeeing it was their duty to ſhew or ſet forth the Lords death, and to keepe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne commemoration of it till his ſecond comming, it was alſo their duty in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> to examine themſelves, and participate the Sacrament, notwithſtanding the abuſive and dangerous comming in of others; &amp; ſo alſo in our publike Aſſemblies and Ordinances, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Lord may and will bring judgement both temporall and ſpirituall upon the heads of them that vilifie his Ordinances, yet it being our duty to keepe ſolemne commemoration of the death of our Lord Chriſt till his ſecond comming, we alſo ought to examine our ſelves, labour for Sacramentall qualifications, which I hope are not unknowne to thoſe that are fit communicants, and ſo to eate and ſo to drinke, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Argument.</p>
               <p>Not to put difference betweene the precious and the vile, is a ſinne: but Gods people in the Sacrament by comming with wicked men doe not put difference betweene the precious and the vile: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The ſinne of not putting difference betweene the precious and the vile, is charged upon the Prieſts under the Law, and ſo upon thoſe under the Goſpel, which have power to receive or caſt out,<note place="margin">Ezek. 44. and 22.2.</note> not upon the people or private Chriſtians: but now in caſe thoſe in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be corrupt or neglect their duty in not exerciſing diſciplin, this gives me no warrant to ſeparate, no more then when the Prieſts under the Law profaned the Ordinances by admitting perſons uncircumciſed and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy into the Aſſemblies, gave any warrant to the people of God to turne their backes upon his publike Ordinances, of which there is no example in all the booke of God.</p>
               <p>For though the vile ought not to come, yet the precious may and ought to come to the Ordinances of God in ſtrength of duty to God and for their owne benefit: and though it will be ſaid it is not lawfull to give holy things to Dogges, or childrens bread, yet I hope holy perſons and children themſelves may participate freely of thoſe things that are provided for them; It were a very ridiculous thing if I ſhould ſee one caſting a peece of bread, though it were never ſo good, nay though it were a whole loafe to Dogges, for me to reſolve, Well, I ſaw ſuch a one throwing good bread to Dogges fit for men to eate, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will never more eate bread while I live, nor come where bread is.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I confeſſe Gods people, private Chriſtians ought to put diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the precious and the vile, and though they doe come
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:155268:18"/> to the Sacrament in mixt Aſſemblies if they obſerve the cautions for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly given by ſhowing their diſlike of ſuch abuſes, mourning for them, by ſeaſonable exhortations, reproofes, or admonitions, labour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation according to the bounds &amp; limits of their places &amp; callings, obſerving circumſtances of time, place, perſon, &amp;c. and by their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God for reformation herein, though they doe come with wicked men to the Sacrament, they doe put an apparent difference betweene the precious and the vile.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Though it be a ſinne not to put difference betweene the precious and the vile this way, their ſeparation is but adding one ſinne to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and no way cleares them of the guilt of ſinne, but increaſes it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have no warrant to ſeparate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Argument.</p>
               <p>That that's neither commanded by God in Scripture, nor neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly implyed, that is unlawfull to practiſe: but that Godly men ſhall partake of the Sacrament of the Lords ſupper in mixt Aſſemblies is neither commanded in Scripture, nor neceſſarily implied: therefore the practiſe thereof is unlawfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is both commanded and neceſſarily and ſtrongly implied, and therefore it is lawfull to practiſe, and our duty ſo to doe: that it is commanded will appeare thus, and therefore neceſſarily implied, where Scripture is more ſilent.</p>
               <p>Firſt, conſider what hath beene ſaid concerning the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> how corrupt it was both in Doctrine and Diſcipline, and yet the Apoſtle laies an Apoſtolike command upon them, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theſe corruptions and corrupt members they ſhould in ſtrength of their duty examine, and eate, &amp;c. <hi>Let a man [therefore] examine himſelfe:</hi> therefore, Wherefore? becauſe many come unpreparedly and unworthily to their owne deſtruction and condemnation, therefore doe you examine your ſelves, and ſo eate of this bread and drinke of this cup: and that this his Apoſtolike injunction might take the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter effect with them, he firſt ſhowes them his authority.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.23. 1 Cor. 11.24.25.</note>1. That what he delivered to them he received from the Lord Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In ſo doing they ſhould anſwer the end of the inſtitution in that there by they ſhew the Lords death, and keepe a continuall comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of it till his ſecond comming.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ma. 26.26.27, 28.</note>Chriſt ſaith alſo, <hi>Take, eate, this is my body, &amp;c.</hi> and our Saviour Chriſt in the inſtitution of it ſaith expreſſely <hi>[doe this] in remembrance of me,</hi> yea even when <hi>Judas</hi> himſelfe was knowne to them all to be the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:155268:18"/> betrayer of Chriſt after Chriſt had told them, yea and <hi>Judas</hi> himſelfe of his treaſon, he bleſſed the bread, brake it, and bid them all eate of it, and tooke the cup and bid them all drinke of it, &amp;c. now if a know no hypocrite, a knowne Devill, a knowne betrayer of Chriſt were among the 12. Diſciples at the Sacrament, nay at the inſtitution of it when it was moſt free of corruption, and yet this ſinne of <hi>Judas</hi> never at all charged upon the reſt though they then all knew him, ſurely a knowne profane perſon may be at the Lords Table, and yet godly men may lawfully participate, and his ſinne not charged upon the reſt, nor hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them from the benefit of the Ordinances.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> There was but one of twelve wicked, but in our Aſſemblies are above twelve wicked to one godly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If there were one of twelve whom Chriſt himſelfe choſe, who knew the hearts of all men, well may there be twelve for one when cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt men that can ſee no further then the outſide, nor have no power nor will ſometimes to reforme that, have to doe in admitting or keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backe; and when men of all ſorts that profeſſe Chriſt, come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without an immediate call from Chriſt as the Diſciples had: one Devill among twelve choſen Diſciples choſen by Chriſt is more then one thouſand in other Aſſemblies: and ſurely if Chriſt had ſeene the being of an hypocrite or devill amongſt them could have made the aſſembly unlawfull or taken away the benefit of the Sacrament from them, he would never have choſen <hi>Judas</hi> to be one of the twelve, or at leaſt would never admitted him to the Sacrament; for though at firſt the Diſciples knew not <hi>Judas</hi> to bee an hypocrite, yet Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe knew him, and a knowne hypocrite ought to be as well kept from the ordinances as a knowne prophaned perſon, and is a more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous perſon in the Church. So if our Miniſters or men that have power in the Church ſhould know a man to be a groſſe hypocrite, they ought to be as ſhye and carefull to caſt him out as a common drunkard or adulterer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2.</hi> It is neceſſarily implied, and more.</p>
               <p>By the example of all Apoſtolike Churches who had all of them corrupt members, and corruptions in them, in Doctrinein, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, yet I never read of any that were beleeving that ever ſeparated or had any toleration ſo to doe; indeed the Apoſtle ſaith they went out from us becauſe they were not of us,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> if they had beene of us they would have continued with us: falſe hearted profeſſors fell off and departed, but no believer, no Saint ſeparated. I ſpeake now no more how they were corrupted both the Church of the Jewes, <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:155268:19"/> Galatia,</hi> and the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> of that heretofore; in <hi>Corinth</hi> there was that abuſe that I never ſaw in our Aſſemblies, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament given to a drunkard in his drunkenneſſe, as we ſee the text is there plaine for it, Some came hungry, ſome drunke; or drunkards have a little more ſhame, though they be drunke weeke after weeke, and day after day, yet when they come to the Lords table, they will be ſome body, for ſhame they will not then be drunke; if they were I thinke none would be ſo madde as to give the Sacrament to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond thing conſiderable is to ſhew the lawfulneſſe of joyning in mixt Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, the premiſes conſidered with thoſe cautions formerly delivered, and it will appeare lawfull if we conſider theſe particulars enſuing.</head>
               <p>Firſt, As I have ſaid no place or part of Gods word doth forbid it, for though ſome places of Scripture have ſome ſemblance that way, yet when I come to that particular to anſwer them it will appeare other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes.</p>
               <p>Secondly, As we have proved we have Gods command for it, as the former inſtance of Chriſt and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, The example of Gods people in all ages; ſee <hi>Elkanah</hi> and <hi>Hannah</hi> under the law. See the Jewes alſo in the Prophets time, none decline the publike aſſemblies of Gods worſhip, ordinances, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, though as hath beene largely proved both Prieſt and people were corrupt in Doctrine and Diſcipline, yea alſo in their converſations. See this alſo in the Apoſtolike Churches before alledged.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, It is our duty to come to the ordinances if we would have benefit by them: <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.25. the Apoſtle exhorts to this duty, and reproved them that did forſake the Aſſembly.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, The ſinnes of others are not charged upon us if we come duly prepared and as we ought to doe.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, The errors of the governours of the Church are not made over to particular members, no more then the ſins of <hi>Elies</hi> ſons was upon <hi>Elkanab</hi> and <hi>Hannah,</hi> or the reſt of Gods people.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, The uſes, ends and effects of the ordinances are obtained in mixt aſſemblies, which are ſuch as theſe following.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. To ſtrengthen our faith and other graces.</item>
                  <item>2. To renew our Covenant with God.</item>
                  <item>3. To commemorate the death of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: all which may be attained, notwithſtanding the preſence of wicked men at the ordinances.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:155268:19"/>
               <p>Eighthly, We cannot, as hath beene proved, be ſaid to joyne with wicked men in the ordinances though we be preſent with them, the premiſes conſidered.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, My owne preparation and examination makes me wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and capable of the ordinances, the ſinfullneſſe and unpreparedneſſe of others makes me not uncapable: To the pure, all things are pure,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.15.</note> but unto them that are defiled and unbeleeving, nothing is pure, but even their mindes and conſciences are defiled.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, It is one thing for a man to joyne himſelfe with a congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Idolaters in their Idolatrous worſhips and wages, another thing for a prophane man to joyne himſelfe, nay rather thruſt himſelfe among Gods people exerciſed in and about the ordinances of God.</p>
               <p>Eleventhly, No example in Scripture of any that ever ſeparated from the publike aſſemblies of Gods worſhip. I ſtand not now to prove whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our aſſemblies are ſo becauſe of that heretofore.</p>
               <p n="12">12. That which ſometimes and in ſome reſpect may be unlawfull, in ſome other reſpect becomes lawfull,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5 9.10, 11. 2 Theſ. 3.14.</note> as <hi>Davids</hi> eating the ſhewbread in caſe of neceſſity. So I am commanded not to eate with an inordinate brother, but rather then I will ſtarve for food I may eate with him; I ought not to have to doe with wicked men at all if I could avoyd it, but if my calling compell me I am permitted: now if the neceſſity of the body alter the caſe and make things lawfull that are otherwayes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull much more the neceſſity of the ſoule: now we know there is a neceſſity laid upon Gods people either to partake in mixt aſſemblies at the Sacrament, or they cannot enjoy the benefit of the ordinances,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.35.</note> the food and nouriſhment of the Soule, unleſſe they will ſeparate which they have no warrant for.<note place="margin">Eph. 3.17. Joh. 6.56. 1 Joh. 4.13</note>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. Nothing can ſeparate betweene Chriſt the head and the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Chriſtian. Chriſt dwells in the beleever and the beleever in Chriſt, therefore it is neither man nor devill, death, ſinne, nor hell can ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them, much leſſe the company of prophane men that thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves amongſt Gods people in the Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Had it beene unlawfull abſolutely to participate in mixt aſſemblies either our Lord Chriſt or the Apoſtle would have laid a prohibition upon it, for there is nothing of abſolute neceſſity for a Chriſtian man to know and practice tending to life and ſalvation but it is revealed in the word of God by precept or example; nor no fundamentall error but it is alſo therein forbidden.</p>
               <p n="15">15.<note place="margin">Exek. 18.14.</note> God is juſt and he puniſhes not one man for the ſinnes of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unleſſe he make them, his by conſenting to them and liking or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:155268:20"/> approving them, which none of Gods people doe by the ſinnes of wicked men in the Sacrament: <hi>(The ſoule that ſinneth ſhall die.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.4, 5.</note>16. It is agreeable to the rule to caſt out the offender, but not for the innocent to caſt out themſelves, there is no rule for that.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.14</note>17. Unbeleevers thruſting in themſelves, gives them no fellowſhip with the Saints, for they can have no fellowſhip with them.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Errors in diſcipline, nay in many points of doctrine take not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the uſe of fundamentalls, nor the eſſentialls of a Church.</p>
               <p n="19">19. He that is caſt out of the Church is delivered up to Satan though he be caſt out againſt his will, what becomes then of thoſe that caſt out themſelves (conſider;) truely unleſſe God have more care to preſerve them from the ſnares of Satan then they bewray herein, they would become a very prey to the devill.</p>
               <p n="20">20. That expoſition of Scripture which is unreaſonable is falſe: but to ſay the Apoſtle would have us not at all to company with wicked men in the Sacrament, or that we ſhould deprive our ſelves of the meanes of life and ſalvation, and of the benefit of the ordinance, by reaſon of the preſence of wicked men who deprive themſelves thereof, this is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and ſo falſe expoſition of Scripture, and an unſound con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                  </label> If we were yet convinced that it were our duty to partake in ſuch mixt aſſemblies we would doe it, but that's yet the queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> If all that hath beene already ſaid be not enough, conſider;</p>
               <p>Firſt, it is our duty to feed upon Chriſt by Faith in the Sacrament, therefore as we regard the thriving of our ſoules, we ought not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them the meanes of grace,<note place="margin">Joh. 6.55.</note> leſt the guilt of periſhing lie upon our owne heads: the fleſh of Chriſt is meat indeed and his blood drinke indeed, the fleſh and blood of Chriſt is the reall food of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it is the command of God, of Chriſt, of the Apoſtle, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our duty as hath beene proved.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, we have the example of Gods people in former ages to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry us thorow it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, if it be our duty to commemorate the death of Chriſt, it is our duty to receive the Sacrament though prophaners bee there preſent.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, the Apoſtle gives us order to examine our ſelves and eate, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe this as a remedy againſt the abuſes and diſorders in the Church. I conclude therefore thus that it is lawfull to participate in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, where prophane perſons are not caſt out, as from all that hath been ſaid ſo briefely, from there two Arguments.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:155268:20"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>1</label> That that cannot deprive us of the maine ends and benefit of our performances ought not to deterre us from them: but the preſence of wicked men at the Sacrament cannot deprive us of the benefit and ends of the Sacrament: therefore ought not to deterre us and keepe us backe from the Sacrament.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>2</label> That which God commands and expects from his people, and hath beene the lawfull practiſe of Gods people in former ages, this his people are ſtill bound to doe.</p>
               <p>But God by Chriſt and the Apoſtle commands us to receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, &amp; Gods people have practiſed it in former ages, and that law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in ſtrength of duty, notwithſtanding wicked and prophane men have bin amongſt them in all times: therfore it is the duty of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in our times alſo. I ceaſe to preſſe it with more arguments, though all the former particulars may be drawne into ſo many ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but I hope they will ſuffice being well conſidered, as particulars of concernment to the purpoſe in hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                  </label> There are divers godly and learned Miniſters that refuſe to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Sacrament upon this ground, ſurely if it were not ſinfull and unlawfull to adminiſter it in a mixt aſſembly they would not refuſe to doe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I know and am confident that many both godly and learned have laid aſide the adminiſtration of the Sacrament by reaſon of that ſinfull mixture of holy, and prophane at that ſacred ordinance; and I beleeve they are men of able parts, qualified and gifted from God, lawfully called to diſpenſe his ordinances, yet their conſciences are tender this way, and therefore have forborne to adminiſter, and though I dare not condemne them of any ſinfull neglect herein, yet I cannot nor dare juſtifie their practiſe; neither would I ſeeme more knowing then they to whom the Lord hath given greater light, onely by the way I deſire to ſpeake my owne thoughts of it with ſubjection to better judgements.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I anſwer that as there are many godly and learned Miniſters that have upon this ground laid aſide the adminiſtration of this ſacred ordinance; ſo there are as many, and farre more in number as learned and as godly that notwithſtanding this corrupt mixture yet doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the diſpenſation thereof.<note place="margin">Prov. 27.23. Acts 20.28. 1 Pet. 5.2.3. Ezek. 34.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, we muſt conſider that there is in a Miniſter or Paſtor of a Congregation required not onely Miniſteriall and Sacramentall qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications for himſelfe, that he may become a worthy Communicant, but a charge lies upon him alſo to looke well to the flocke, over which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:155268:21"/> the holy Ghoſt hath placed him, that they alſo may be ſuch as have right and intereſt to the ſeales and Sacraments of life and ſalvation: therefore he ought to be very carefull of them to inſtruct them concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the author, inſtitution and end of this Sacrament, and what the Lord requires of all that deſire to participate to his glory and their owne comforts. Alſo he ought to ſhew them the great and ineſtimable benefit of worthy receiving, and the extreame and inevitable danger that enſues upon ſinfull, prophane, unprepared, and unworthy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching the table of the Lord: yea he ought to have power to caſt out offenders of this nature. But now in caſe when he hath done his duty in ſeaſonable exhortations, admonitions, inſtructions, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes, that the governement of the Church be ſo corrupt that the Diſciples thereof be wreſted out of his hands, into ſuch hands as are as corrupt and vaine as thoſe that ought to be caſt out of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, yea and that by conſent of the publike or ſupreme Magiſtrate, the queſtion is whether in this caſe it is more lawfull to deſiſt the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, or to continue the diſpenſation thereof in a mixt Aſſembly. For my owne part I conceive it more lawfull to continue the uſe and adminiſtration thereof, then to deſiſt it, and that from theſe groundes following.</p>
               <p>Firſt, It will appeare by all that hath beene formerly ſaid concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joyning or participating in mixt Aſſemblies at the Sacrament, that the ſinne of ſuch as come irreverently, and unworthily unto this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, cannot be charged upon either miniſter or people, that come themſelves as they ought: And diſcharging their duty in uſing all lawfull meanes to prevent this abuſe, as when neither exhortation, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, or reproofe, promiſes, or denunciations will take place, when the power of diſcipline is corrupt as aforeſaid, then praying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt and mourning for ſuch abuſes and abominations in the Church,<note place="margin">Ezek. 9.4, 6.</note> is expected from Gods people, not a Ceſſation of the diſpenſation of ſuch precious ordinances.</p>
               <p>Secondly, If Gods miniſters have power, as I know nothing to the contrary, to call Gods people together to diſtribute to them the ſeales of the Covenant, why doe they deny them that priviledge to whom it eſpecially and properly belongs, and for whom it was princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally ordained: though they deny it to ſuch as have no right to it? If they are not able to know what all men are, yet let them adminiſter it to thoſe they are well perſwaded of, and lay a generall charge upon ſuch as by reaſon of our great Aſſemblies, they cannot be ſo well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted withall, who in Judgement of Charity may have right alſo,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:155268:21"/> and let them have the like priviledge till their lives give teſtimony to the contrary: For as wee were better in our almes to relieve ten coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeits, then let Chriſt goe naked or hungry in any one member, ſo had we better to admit ten Hypocrites to the Table of the Lord then deprive one godly man of this ſoule nouriſhment; it is true our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Caſt not Pearles before Swine, nor holy things to Dogs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth 7.6.</note> that is ſpoken as well of the doctrine of the Goſpell as of the Sacrament, yea and more properly, Chriſtian exhortations, admonitions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes are there meant, as appeares by the following words, <hi>Leſt they turne againe and all to rent you,</hi> or leſt they ſpurne at and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject your reproofes, admonitions, and you alſo. This alſo is of the ſame importance, Reject him that is an heretique,<note place="margin">Tit. 3.10.</note> after the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond admoniſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion: both places import thus much, that if wicked men would with patience and meekeneſſe receive and heare the word of God with Chriſtian admonitions, &amp;c. and not reſiſt and reject them, they might receive the benefit of them, and though they might be yet uncapable of the Sacrament; that which I infer from that place of Scripture is, that it hath no relation at all to the Sacrament more then to other holy ordinances. Secondly, that though we ought not to give holy things to dogs nor Pearles to Swine, yet holy perſons &amp; thoſe to whom ſuch precious mercies belong, ought not to be denyed them; &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the firſt inference ſhould bee denied concerning the relation of that place of <hi>Matthew</hi> to the Sacrament, yet no reaſonable man can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the latter.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.24, 25, 26. 1 Cor. 11.28. 1 Cor 11.26. Matth. 26.26, 27, 28.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3ly. Conſider the command of our Saviour Chriſt for the performance of this duty, <hi>Doe this in remembrance of me,</hi> and ſo alſo we have an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicke injunction for it: <hi>Let a man examine himſelfe and ſo let him eate of this bread and drinke of this cup:</hi> alſo conſider the uſe and end of its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; <hi>for as oft as yee eate of this bread and drinke of this cup yee ſhow the Lords death till he come:</hi> &amp; ſo alſo, <hi>drinke ye all of it, for this is my blood of the new Teſtament that is ſhed for many for the remiſſion of ſinnes:</hi> and in the ſame place concerning the bread he ſaith, <hi>Take, eate, this is my body, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, wee have the example as of all Gods people in all ages partaking in mixt aſſemblies, ſo of Gods Prieſts and Miniſters in all times, yea in the Apoſtolike Churches of <hi>Corinth, Galatia,</hi> the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> the Church of the Jewes, under the Law, yea alſo in our owne Congregations ſince the reformation of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper hath beene received in mixt aſſemblies, as hath beene already largely proved, and if Gods people have received it in mixt aſſemblies, by conſequence, Gods Prieſts and Miniſters have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered it in mixt aſſemblies; indeed God blames the Prieſts under the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:155268:22"/> Law for admitting people uncircumciſed to his holy ordinances, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver for giving holy things to holy perſons or to any that were in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Communion with them, though doubtleſſe many of them were vitious in their lives. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth not ſay if the inceſtuous perſon or thoſe drunkards or Schiſmatiques that were in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> were not caſt out that they ſhould ceaſe the publike admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, no not a word to that purpoſe, but uſe all lawfull meanes in our power to purge abuſes of this nature out of the Church, but eſpecially out of our owne hearts: Let every man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, godly Miniſters give occaſion to carnall men to deſpiſe the worke of reformation, while they ſee even thoſe that ſeeme to be moſt forward that way different in their practiſes, ſome deſiſting the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, ſome continuing it. See ſay they what manner of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation theſe men would have, they differ ſo among themſelves, they know not what they would have, ſo hinder the worke of reformation and ſcandall the wayes of God by their diviſions among themſelves, and give great advantage to the adverſaries of our Religion.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, as it is better for Gods ſheepe to feed upon paſture where ſome weeds grow rather then ſtarve for want of food; ſo it is better for Gods ſhepheards to ſuffer ſome weeds to grow in the ſheeps Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, if they cannot prevent it, then to ſtarve their flocke; yea and as it is better for the ſheepe to feed among goates rather then ſtarve, ſo it is better the ſhepheards ſhould ſuffer goates to feed upon the ſheeps paſture though it ſhould poyſon them, then for the ſheepe to be kept from it, it being as I ſaid out of their power to reforme it.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Conſider there is neither command in Scripture nor example of any Prieſt under the Law, or Miniſter or Paſtor under the Goſpell, that upon this or any ſuch ground did lay aſide the adminiſtration of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Ordinances, eſpecially the Sacrament of the Lords Supper. But we ſee it is expreſly commanded to be obſerved, and enjoyned Gods people to frequent, and if Gods people ought not to forſake the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, or the Ordinances, or turne their backes upon them from any ſuch ground, much leſſe ought the Miniſters who by their abſence give a ceſſation to the Ordinances, deprive Gods people of the benefit and uſe of them, for whoſe ſakes they were as I ſaid principally or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Gods Miniſters doe but deſiſt the adminiſtration a while till it pleaſe God to open a doore of enlargement, that power may bee put into their hands to caſt out offenders and to have a people congregated according to God.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:155268:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Wee all ought to labour and indeavour this way both by prayer and all other lawfull meanes to forward this worke of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, but I know no warrant any Miniſter of God hath upon any ſuch ground, to deny either Gods people or themſelves the benefit of this Ordinance, they may as well deſiſt all other publike adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon one and the ſame ground: ſuppoſe divers honeſt men were confined to a place where they could not bee without the company of ungodly men, and that there were a keeper appointed to looke to them to give them that by which their lives and comforts are preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and maintained, what would we thinke of that keeper that would refuſe to adminiſter ſuch things as are of abſolute neceſſitie to preſerve them in health till they come as it were out of priſon to have their ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles ſpread in their owne houſes and families out of ſuch wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed company, not knowing when the time of their confinement would end? ſurely we would conclude him an ignorant or idle fellow that would rather ſuffer them to ſtarve in keeping their allowance from them, then giving it them in an untoward way, or among theeves and robbers; and as fooliſh would they be found, that upon ſuch grounds refuſe to receive their nouriſhment: even ſo though Gods people bee conſtrained either to partake with wicked men at the Lords table or loſe the benefit of it; I hould it a very weake argument that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of wicked men ſhould debarre them of it: ſurely the neceſſity Gods people have of it, the right they have to it, the command of the Lord Chriſt, and apoſtolicall injunction inferring it, together with the example of Gods people in former ages prayſing it, ought to bee more prevailant with miniſters to continue the diſpenſation of it then the unavoydable preſence of wicked men ought to be for the deſiſting of this great Ordinance. Certainly the Lord rather expects men ſhould waite upon him in the Lawfull uſe of meanes in their places and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, indeavouring to obſerve and performe theſe duties in as holy a manner as they can till he open a doore of enlargement, rather then to turne their backs upon ſuch duties of high concernment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Thirdly, I now come to ſpeake to the unlawfulneſſe of ſeparation from our pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like aſſemblies, having already ſufficiently ſpoke to the lawfulneſſe of joyning in them in the Ordinances, notwithſtanding their corruptions in and about the adminiſtrations of them.</head>
               <p>Firſt, conſider we turne our backes upon the Ordinances, of God for as the diſorderly <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſinned in deſpiſing the Church of God by<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.22.</note>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:155268:23"/> their abuſive thruſting themſelves to the Lords Table, ſo they that ſeparate from them doe alſo deſpiſe the Ordinance of God in turning their backes upon them, and are as deepely guilty.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by ſeparating our ſelves we deprive our ſelves of the benefit of the ordinances, and hereby we doe that hurt to our ſelves that wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mens preſence with us could never doe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by departing and ſetting up wayes of our owne wee become guilty of performing our inventions before the ordinance of God, and with <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> offer ſtrange fire, which we know the Lord pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from heaven with fire.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, wee lay our ſelves open to temptation, for certainly if Gods people bee but a while abſent from the publike ordinances of preaching and adminiſtration of the Sacrament or prayer, the great ordinances of the Church, either accidentally by buſineſſe, or voluntarily, if ſuch a thing can bee in Gods people, what abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of deadneſſe and coldneſſe overſpreads their hearts, how are they diſabled, for dutie publique or private, how unable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt temptation, to wraſtle with their luſts and wicked hearts? and truely if wee bee foyled by ſinne or Satan, the world or our owne heart in the time of our voluntary departing from the meanes of grace, blame our ſelves herein, I appeale to the hearts and conſciences of every godly man that hath experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the frailty of themſelves this way whether it bee thus yea or no.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Wee hereby deny our ſoules of their neceſſary food and nouriſhment; and if it bee a ſinne to neglect the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the body, much more to neglect the welfare of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Wee hereby lay a ſtumbling blocke in the way of weake Chriſtians, who are doubtfull becauſe of our depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Wee open the mouthes not onely of the Papiſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Proteſtant Religion, but of carnall Goſpellers and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill honeſt men, who make this the great Thunder-bolt to ſhoot at our Religion and profeſſion, even the diviſions, diverſitie of opinions, ſeverall ſects that are among ſuch as profeſſe Religion, and this keepes many off from comming on to a Religious way
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:155268:23"/> of life; The Lord of peace ſettle peace amongſt us and make us all of one and the ſame mind, according to truth in the worſhip and ſervice of God.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, Wee doe by our ſeparation ſcandall the Ordinances and whole aſſemblies of the Church; for either the ordinances muſt be Idolatrous, and the aſſembly Idolaters and Antichriſtian, as the Separation of neceſſity muſt call them, and doe, or elſe they know their ſeparation were unlawfull: and herein I feare the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill hath a maine ſtroake by nouriſhing in men ſuch opinions, as I formerly ſaid, while hee appeares in their eſtimation an Angell of light, for certainly this is a more dangerous Rent hee makes in the Church then any other can bee, for hee divides now not Papiſts from Proteſtants, nor prophane perſons from holy, which may bee done in the exerciſe of the Ordinances of our publique aſſemblies, but hee now divides and ſowes diſcord and diſſention betweene the godly themſelves. I pray God make us all wiſe to diſcerne and avoyd his ſubtiltie. Certainly if wee ought not to receive accuſation againſt an Elder under two or three Witneſſes,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.9.</note> how much more carefull ought wee to bee to have very ſtrong proofes and arguments to make good an accuſation, yea ſuch a foul one as this is againſt a whole Church or Congregation, ſome of whom our owne hearts tell us are in the number of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and truely ſo accounted? nay the ſcandall reſts not onely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Gods people, but upon the Ordinances of God alſo, for all that ſeparate muſt account them Idolaters, elſe their ſeparation is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, it will appeare, it is unlawfull to ſeparate from ſuch aſſemblies as ours are where the Word and Doctrine of ſalvation is ſo plentifully taught, the Sacraments ſo duely adminiſtred, ſuch a viſible profeſſion made to both theſe, notwithſtanding the corruptions among us; by theſe things to which the Church of God is compared in Scripture.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to a Vine: I am the Vine, ſaith the Lord Chriſt, and yee are the branches, <hi>John</hi> 15.5. Now in caſe there bee a dead fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe branch or more, what courſe is to bee taken? What, cut off the living branches? Nay,<note place="margin">Iohn 15 2</note> cut off the dead branches that the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving may thrive the better: Every branch that beareth not fruite hee taketh away, ſaith the Lord Chriſt, meaning God the Father, who is the Husbandman; and every branch that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:155268:24"/> bringeth forth fruit he purgeth that it may bring forth more fruit.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 20.1. Eſa 5.1. 1 Cor. 3.9.</note>Secondly, The Church of God is Gods vineyard, Gods husbandry, the Lord he preſerves the vines, the young trees, the flowers, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable hearbs, but he takes away and rootes up the dead branches, weeds and ſuch like, and ſurely we would count him a mad vine-dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer or gardner that becauſe of ſome dead branches in the vine or ſome weeds in the garden, ſhould thinke to make the vine fruitfull by cutting off the living fruitfull branches, and the garden to proſper by plucking up the hearbes and flowers, this indeed is the way to deſtroy a vine, a husbandry, a garden, but never a way to preſerve it: and truely the next way to give a nullity to a Church, is for every godly man, if they durſt, to ſeparate from it, and ſtrip it of its Ordinances, and Members, but the way to preſerve it is to purge it by caſting out the abuſive, not by departing from it: it is needleſſe here to aske mee what wee ſhould doe, if thoſe dead branches be not cut off, I have already anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.9.</note>Thirdly, Compared to a building; in buildings we know men uſe to caſt away refuſe rotten Timber and rubbidge, but they make uſe of the ſound and ſerviceable materials, or elſe they would make but a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh building.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, To a body whereof Jeſus Chriſt is head: now we know a man may be a true man and have a palſie hand,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.4, 5. 1 Cor. 6.15 Epheſ. 5 30.</note> or a rotten finger, and the way to preſerve life is to cut off the dead rotten member, not to cut off the ſound; if there ſhould be any of that other opinion, I ſhould as the proverbe ſaith, count him a good Chirurgion, but a very bad Phyſitian.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 13.24, 25.</note>Fifthly, to a field wherein is Cockle as well as corne, Tares as well as Wheate: And though ſome hold that this parable hath relation to the whole world, and by Kingdome of heaven is meant the Goſpell of the kingdome, yet it may as rightly be applyed to the condition of the viſible Church, which ſhall conſiſt of Tares as well as Wheate to the end of the world. Yet take it which way ye will, ſee the Lord of the Harveſt is very carefull to preſerve the Wheate, and therefore would not have the Tares medled withall till harveſt, not that I would ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it as that prophane men in the Church ſhould not be dealt withal, but to this purpoſe, to let men know, the way to preſerve a Church is not by plucking up the godly, or the Wheate, but rather to roote out the Tares, the weedes, the ungodly, and let the good Corne ſtand and grow till harveſt to be gathered into Gods barne.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, The Ordinances in the Church, as the Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:155268:24"/> and Prayer, are compared to the Wedding Feaſt, to which a man ſhould bring his wedding garment, when in that Parable of the marriage of the Kings Sonne, the King came in, he never reproved them that ſat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at table that had on theſe Wedding garments, but him that had none, takes him and caſts him out, the reſt were not ſhut from the table, becauſe they ſate with him that had not on his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor reproved for it, he ſinned, and he onely ſuffered: ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, the beleeving prepared Communicant, ſhall not be blamed for the unbeleeving and impenitent, but his ſin ſhall be upon his owne head. And as the ſinnes of wicked men and their preſence at the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament cannot hinder the godly from eating the fleſh and drinking the blood of Chriſt ſpiritually by faith, ſo they can no way hinder the beleever from life and ſalvation,<note place="margin">Joh. 6.54.</note> by this their ſpirituall feeding upon Chriſt, Whoſoever eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh but have everlaſting life.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, It will appeare it is unlawfull to ſeparate from our viſible and publicke a ſemblies, becauſe the Lord continues his preſence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, Let no man be more holy than God. For ſo long as the Word and Sacraments are continued, and the viſible ſignes of Gods gracious preſence making the meanes effectuall to convert and build up in the wayes of God, as, the Lord be praiſed, wee have ſufficient proofe dayly of, we may conclude it is utterly unlawfull to ſeparate. They themſelves that do ſeparate do confeſſe they had their converſion in our aſſemblies, and their beginnings of grace, though ſome of them evade it and ſay, not by the meanes in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but by reading and private conference, and the like; but we have daily ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient and good teſtimony of the benefit received by the Ordinances and meanes of grace, continued in our publique aſſemblies, I hope eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry godly heart among us hath large teſtimony of the daily heate, life, and comfort that is found in them: we finde that propheſie in the 42 of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and the 16. verſe, fulfilled to us: and ſo <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 29.18. where the Lord by the Prophet foretells what he would doe for his people under the Goſpell, he would bring the blinde by a way they knew not, that he would make darkeneſſe light before them, and crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed things ſtraight: ſo in that 29. Chapter, In that day ſhall the deafe heare the words of the booke, and the eyes of the blinde ſhall ſee out of obſcurity, and out of darkeneſſe, &amp;c. And truely the proofe of the efficacy of the meanes of grace in our publique aſſemblies, hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the witneſſe of many hundreds who have ſuffered perſecution for it, and have, many of them, ſealed it with their deareſt blood, who
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:155268:25"/> doubtleſſe are now enjoying the bleſſed fruites of their ſufferings, for the name, profeſſion, and Goſpel of Chriſt: none of all which Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, did ever account in the Church of <hi>England</hi> the Ordinances of God Idolatrous or Antichriſtian, or till it did wholly apoſtate, and as it now ſtands it was in Kings <hi>Edwards</hi> time.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 9.25.32.</note>What better witneſſe can there be than experience? or how is the tree knowne but by its fruites? this perſwaded the blinde man of the truth of Chriſts Doctrine, even the miracle that he wrought upon him: Surely, ſaith he, God heares not ſinners, and I am ſure I once was blinde, and I now ſee; as I hope many of us in our aſſemblies can ſay, whoſe eyes the Lord hath opened, and whoſe hearts the Lord hath changed. Let the Separation raile upon our Ordinances, Miniſters, and Aſſemblies as much as the Scribes and Phariſees againſt Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and Diſciples, and labour to ſeduce men as they would have done the blinde man whoſe eyes he had opened; I ſay, let them do what they will to reproach us, we may truely ſay, once we were blind and we now ſee, and we are ſure the Lord hath opened our Eyes by this contemptible meanes: and as by vertue of Chriſts prayer, the clay and ſpittle became effectuall, ſo by vertue of the Spirit of God, and the Interceſſion of Jeſus Chriſt, for his poore Saints, the meanes of grace becomes effectuall, both to convert, and to confirme and eſtabliſh to eternall life.</p>
               <p>By workes, Saint <hi>James</hi> ſaith, faith is made manifeſt, or perfect, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.22. and ſo our Saviour ſaith, The workes which I doe, teſtifie of me; and as the miracles and great workes of Chriſt ought to have convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Jewes that he was Chriſt, ſo the many yeares large and plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fruite reaped by the publique adminiſtrations of the Ordinances in our publique aſſemblies ought to be ſufficient to convince all gaineſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that deny the truth and lawfulneſſe of them, for ſurely were not the preſence and power of God in the Ordinances they would become dead and fruitleſſe.</p>
               <p n="11">11. If a man were deſirous to ſeparate, and that it were lawfull, where is the Word of God, the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt, more fully, clearely, truely, and powerfully preached than in our publique aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and in many places the Sacraments as duely and reverently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred? And I am confident there are as few falſe-hearted profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> conſidering the proportion, as in the moſt exact aſſembly of ſeparation: by Profeſſors, are meant not onely ſuch as are in externall Communion, but ſuch as ſeem in a more ſpeciall manner to performe godlineſſe, and of theſe for uprightneſſe, they may
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:155268:25"/> ſet forth to moſt exact aſſemblies, &amp;c. of ſeparation.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Conſider Salvation is to be had in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by the meanes of grace continued in it, therefore it is a true Church, and unlawfull to ſeparate from it, and to turne our backes upon the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> We that ſeparate, doe not turne our backes upon the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, but we deſire to enjoy them with more purity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is lawfull to deſire and indevour this way, but let no man be more holy than God commands him, nor doe unlawfull actions that a good end may be produced out of it.</p>
               <p>Let any man ſhew me where Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e allowes of, or commands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch ſeparation from a true Church, for any ſuch ends, and I ſhall be ſilent: it is true, there are many places pointing out Gods people to ſeparate from heathens, publike Idolaters and Idolatrous worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, but never did I read that one Jew ſeparated from the publique aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of Jewes, nor one Chriſtian warranted to ſeparate from the publique aſſemblies of that Church of which hee is a member, borne of Chriſtian parents, which were members of this Church, and themſelves admitted members by baptiſme into the viſible aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of Gods worſhip and ordinances, that ſuch a one ſhould rip himſelfe from the publike aſſemblies of Gods people for any errour in Doctrine or Diſcipline, eſpecially not fundamentall,<note place="margin">1 Tim 2.1.2. Deut. 17.18 Ioſu. 3.6. and 6.6. 1 King. 2.35. 2 King. 18.4. 1 Chron. 13.12. &amp; 15 1.11.12.16. 2 Chron. 8.14. &amp; 17.6, 7, 8, 9. &amp; 19.18. Mat. 22.21. Rom. 13.1, 2. 1 Pet. 2.13. Mat. 10.23</note> or though it be fundamentall, if not the errour of the whole Church, it gives no warrant to ſeparate; for I doe not account the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate opinions of ſome of our Divines, who are corrupt in ſome tenents, as that of <hi>Arminius, Pelagius, Socinus, &amp;c.</hi> to bee the errour of the whole Church. For many hundreds for one, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime theſe errours, both clergy and Laity; they have no calling to create a Church to themſelves without conſent of authority, the civill Magiſtrate having power both, as I conceive, to eſtabliſh and reforme Religion, and ſo long as he doth do it according to God we muſt obey actively, if he derogates, then we muſt obey paſſively: if the Magiſtrate command me to heare the Word, to obſerve the Sabbath, &amp;c. I am bound in conſcience, I conceive, to obey; but if he command me to goe to maſſe, I may and ought to refuſe but not reſiſt, obey paſſively, in this as in all other, I ſubject to better judgements; Yet I hold it alſo lawfull to flie rather then reſiſt or ſuffer, but this flying I account is paſſive alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:155268:26"/>
               <head>Fourthly, I come now to ſpeake ſomething of thoſe places of Scripture alledged for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e maintaining of theſe errors of ſeparation.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 33.28 From the matter</note>Firſt, <hi>Numb.</hi> 2.34. the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did according to all that <hi>Moſes</hi> commanded them from the Lord, ſo they pitched by their ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dards, and ſo they ſet forward every one after their Families accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the houſe of their Fathers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I know not at all what relation this hath to the matter in hand or how to conclude a ſeparation lawfull from hence, and though the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did obſerve Gods direction in their journeys, yet many of them were wicked enough in their lives, and yet the other ſeparated not from them; if they would conclude from hence that Chriſtians ſhould undertake nothing under the Goſpel, but what they have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from God for, in matter of worſhip or otherwiſe, then I conclude they muſt not ſeparate becauſe God never commands that we ſhould ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from the publique aſſemblies of his people; but I will ceaſe to ſpeake any thing at all to thoſe places of leſſe concernment, onely quote them in the Margent, that the Reader may peruſe them himſelfe, and ſpeake to thoſe which ſeeme to have more ſtrength.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 7.6, 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
                  </note>Secondly, <hi>Levit.</hi> 20.26. and yee ſhall be holy unto me, for I the Lord your God am holy, and have ſevered you from other people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is farre from the matter in hand; here is a command to <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be holy becauſe God their God is holy, and had ſevered them from other heathen and Idolatrous nations, what warrant this gives one Jew to ſeparate from another, or one godly man to ſeparate from publique aſſemblies of Gods worſhip I know not: our Saviour Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yes the ſame command upon his Diſciples, and ſo upon us, to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he is holy, and he choſe his Diſciples out of the world, doth this give them warrant to ſeparate one from another? all true beleevers are choſen out of the world, that is, from the common ſinfull courſes, cuſtomes and faſhions of the world, yet they ought to hold fellowſhip in the worſhip of God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.2. the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> are blamed for a ſinfull mingling themſelves, which were the holy ſeed, with the Idolatrous and heathen nations that worſhip Idols and falſe gods, Sunne, Moone, Planets, &amp;c. and that in an eſpeciall manner prohibited, <hi>viz.</hi> marrying with them. This is unſutable to the occaſion it is quoted for: if wee worſhip Idols or our ordinances be Idolatrous in their inſtitution, then it were to ſome purpoſe, <hi>John</hi> 15.19. Becauſe I have choſen you out of the world, therefore the world hate you.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:155268:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> All Gods people are choſen out of the world, and upon the ſame ground are hated by the world; doth this give any liberty to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the ordinances?</p>
               <p>Fourthly, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9, 10. But ye are a royall Prieſt-hood, a choſen Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Text hath reference to all the elect of God, as appeares in the firſt Chapter and firſt Verſe, to ſtrangers ſcattered throughout <hi>Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Bithynia,</hi> who were converted and hath no relation at all to a Sacramentall Communion or Church fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, onely intimates all beleevers are choſen, and peculiar to God, which we deny not in oppoſition to the vaſt multitudes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanors in the world.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 23.19. <hi>Jehojada</hi> appointed Porters to the houſe of the Lord, that none that was uncleane ſhould enter in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Put caſe that Leviticall cleanſings, and purifications were not now out of date: yet this is not to the purpoſe: For if he had ſet Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to keepe out the cleane from the ordinances, becauſe of ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane among them that were already entred in, it had beene ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, though but a little to this purpoſe, by reaſon many things, and many men at ſome times were then accounted uncleane, that now are not to be counted uncleane under the Goſpell: as by touching a dead carkas, or having an iſſue of ſeed, &amp;c. theſe are cleane under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, which were then uncleane.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 44.9. No ſtranger uncircumciſed in heart or in fleſh ſhould enter into the Sanctuary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though no ſtranger ſhould enter, becauſe they were not in the limits of the nationall Covenant of circumciſion, yet all that were admitted members of the Jewiſh nation by circumciſion were alſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the ordinances, and yet many of them as vicious and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, as hath formerly beene proved, as any in our aſſemblies can be, &amp; we admit none to that ordinance but ſuch as by baptiſme are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted viſible members as they were by circumciſion; and if no ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhould enter into the ſanctuary,<note place="margin">Ezek. 22.26. Lam. 1.10.</note> ſhould not they enter in that were of the ſame nation, and under the ſame covenant? yea doubtleſſe, and if ſtrangers were admitted by the neglect of the Prieſts, as they were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, did this cauſe the other to ſeparate? this is abſurd.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.26. her Prieſts have violated my Law in that they put no difference betweene the holy and prophane.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This was the Prieſts ſinne, but this gave not the people war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to ſeparate, no more than that of <hi>Elies</hi> ſonnes.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:155268:27"/>
               <p>Eighthly, <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 15.19. If thou take away the precious from the vile.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is, if thou ſeparate or caſt out the vile perſons from the precious: for there is a twofold ſeparating; one, when wee caſt out the party from whom we ſeparate, another, when we caſt out our ſelves from them: but the firſt of theſe is here meant;</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe the precious have right to the ordinances and ought not to be caſt out.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe of the words following in the cloſe of the verſe, (Let them returne to thee, but returne not thou to them) <hi>viz.</hi> Let them upon repentance or entring into covenant come againe to thee, and to the ordinances, but doe not thou decline the ordinance to ſuite with their ſinfull manners: [Let them returne to thee] implies, the vile were once with him, and were caſt out.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 22.26.</note>Eighthly, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.23. They ſhall teach my people the difference b tweene the holy and prophane.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, this was the Prieſts office ſo to doe, to ſhow who have right to the Ordinances, who not, and ſo doe our Miniſters now, or ought to doe, but I can heare no Text ſay, yet if the Prieſt put not di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ference betweene the holy and prophane, doe thou ſeparate thy ſelfe and come not to the publique ordinances.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, <hi>Numbers</hi> 19.20.22. Whatſoever the uncleane perſon touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſhall be uncleane.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We have not now under the Goſpell to doe with ſuch ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and Leviticall purifications as then were in uſe, wee are all cleane through the blood of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.17 Luk. 11.41 Ioh. 15.3.</note> wee may now touch a grave, a dead perſon, a Leper, and yet come to the ordinances: we now ſpeake not of ſuch legall ceremonies, but of godlineſſe and holineſſe of life: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe uncleane perſons had their cleanſings, as appeares in the cited Scripture: many men of vicious lives frequented the ſanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and yet were not counted uncleane: beſides, to the pure all things are pure, but to the impure all things are uncleane. Laſtly, we miſtake if we thinke that the uncleane perſon touching the ordinances of God can mak them unclean in themſelves, or to any other then to themſelves: alſo it is to be noted that the uncleanneſſe ſpoken of in this Text is the uncleanneſſe of the body, whereby ſuch a one was made uncapable of humane ſociety, and this uncleanneſſe kept him no more from the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances then from common ſociety; it is the corruption and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravity of the inner man makes men uncapable of the Sacrament, not any defect or uncleanneſſe in the body other then as it is contagious.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:155268:27"/> This Text of Scripture hath no relation at all to a religious ſeparation but a Civill.</p>
               <p n="10">10. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 6.14.17. Thou ſhoweſt mercy to thy ſervants that walke before thee with all their hearts. If this Text have any thing in it to warrant a ſeparation from the ordinances of Chriſt, let the indifferent judge: if any thing concerning Sacramentall communion were here meant, it would rather be a ſilent reproof of them that decline the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; for they cannot be ſaid to walke uprightly with all their hearts before God.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Exodus</hi> 19.5. If yee will obey my voyce, yee ſhall bee a peculiar treaſure unto me. This is a generall promiſe made to all the nation of the Jewes, and ſo to us under the Goſpell, that upon condition of faith and obedience, the Lord will gratiouſly accept of us in his Sonne to bee his; what there is here to countenance ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the publique aſſemblies of Gods worſhip I underſtand not.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 135.4. For the Lord hath choſen <hi>Jacob</hi> to himſelfe; this Text ſhewes how according to the election of grace, he hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the promiſed ſeed, the children of the faithfull out of the world to himſelfe, as well under the Goſpell as under the Law. Theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture therefore ſhould encourage us to walke with God in the frequent uſe of the Ordinances, not to turne our backes upon them. I hope conſidering what hath beene former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, no man will doubt whether the Word and Sacraments in the Church of England bee the Ordinances of God, though there may be ſome miſcariage in the diſpenſation of them: if they ſhould make any ſuch ſcruple;</p>
               <p>Firſt, let them remember they are of the Lord Chriſt his inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by experience wee ſee the Lord graciouſly found preſent in them, as appeares by the daily fruite proceeding from them; ſo that as our Saviour ſaith concerning himſelfe, My works te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie of me, and, The tree is knowne by its fruits, for men gather not grapes of thornes, nor, &amp;c. even ſo the heat, life and nouriſhment which is attained in theſe ordinances declare manifeſtly the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God in them by his Spirit, making them effectuall to all that belong to the election of grace, and ſo conſequently that they are the ordinance of God, ordained for the converting and building up of his people in the wayes of God.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:155268:28"/>13. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. And ſuch were ſome of you, but ye are waſted, but ye are ſanctifie; the Apoſtle here declares the different condition of Gods people; what they were before converſion, what they are after, what they are by nature, what by grace; it is very ſtrange logicke to draw any concluſion from hence to countenance ſeparation from the Church; true, hence we ought to gather that Gods people after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion ought not to live in that ungodly and uncleane way that they did formerly, nor frequent the ſocieties of uncleane and lewd livers, nor run to the ſame exceſſe of riot with them as they did before converſion, but rather now apply themſelves to the ſociety &amp; fellowſhip with god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and holy men,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.22. Titus 3.3, 4, 5.</note> and frequent the ordinances of God, with all due care and diligence, that they might be more and more built up in the wayes of God.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <note place="margin">Ephe. 4.15, 16. <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
                  </note>14. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.19.20. And not holding the head from which all the body by joynts and bones having nouriſhment miniſtred, and knit together increaſeth with the increaſe of God; wherfore if ye be dead with Chriſt from the rudiments of the world, why as though living in the world are ye ſubject to ordinances? The Apoſtle in theſe words ſheweth the errour and vanity of ſuch as were led away by Jewiſh, and heatheniſh obſervations, as new Moones, Sabbath dayes, meates, drinkes, &amp;c. wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Angels, &amp;c. while they neglect the head of the Church, which is the Lord Chriſt: what colour men may here have to ſeparate from the ordinances of God I know not, as for being ſubject to humane ordinances, we muſt not conceive that the Apoſtle meanes we ſhould reſiſt the lawfull power and authority of men ſet over us in Church and Commonwealth,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.</note> for then we ſhould make one Scripture croſſe another, for Saint <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts us to ſubmit to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake. Then by humane ordinances are ſuch here meant as were Heatheniſh and Jewiſh, that were types and ſhadowes of the ſubſtance which could not now be conſiſtent in the Church with the being of Chriſt, not ſuch ordinances as the Word preached, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and Prayer, theſe are the ordinances of God, and not hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ordinances, though there may bee ſome corruptions in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation and adminiſtration of them; yet they being the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God, we ought not to ſeparate from them.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20. Teaching them, to obſerve all things that I have commanded you, and loe I am with you alwayes unto the end of the world, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> What there is here to maintaine a ſeparation from the publike
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:155268:28"/> aſſemblies of Gods people and worſhip, I know not, if Chriſt have left any ſuch command with his Diſciples, ſurely it would be found extant in Scripture, eſpecially a point of ſo high concernment, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22, 23. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1.13. not ſutable to the purpoſe: beſids the command of Chriſt, and the preſence of Chriſt is to be found for the juſtification of thoſe that attend his ordinance. Such other places of Scripture as ſeeme to have more weight in them follow.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.5. For we being many are one body in Chriſt: hence the Separation conclude that all that partake of the Sacrament are of one and the ſame body, and muſt therefore of neceſſitie be Saints at leaſt in outward appearance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. I anſwer, all that come to the Sacrament whether godly or prophane may be accounted members of the ſame viſible body by an externall covenant, being by baptiſme admitted into the fellowſhip of the viſible Church, and making a profeſſion of faith in Chriſt, though their lives are unanſwerable.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Apoſtle when he ſaith here (we) being many are one body in Chriſt, he ſpeakes of that myſticall union that is betweene Chriſt and beleevers, and ſpeakes here of the inviſible Church, not of the viſible, and it will appeare that he ſpake onely of beleevers, becauſe it is unpoſſible for an hypocrite to be joyned to the body of Chriſt, more than a prophane perſon, and doubtleſſe there were hypocrites a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. Yet ſaith he, we being many, are one body in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Admit he ſhould ſpeake of the viſible Church, and that they ought all to be ſuch as in judgement of Charity are Saints, he doth not ſay, if there be any prophane perſon among you, ſeparate or cut your ſelves from the body.</p>
               <p n="17">17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17. For we being many are one bread, and one body, for we are all partakers of that one bread: The Apoſtle here alſo ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that one-neſſe and ſpirituall Communion that all beleevers have with Chriſt the true bread of life, and the true head of that myſtical bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. This Scripture is of the ſame nature with the former, therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken unto.</p>
               <p n="18">18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. If any man that is called a Brother, be a fornicator, or covetous, or an Idolater, or a rayler, or a drunkard, or an extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner, with ſuch a one eate not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true, we ought not willingly to eate with ſuch a one, or to have any voluntary familiarity with him, this place hath no relation at all to the Sacrament.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:155268:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> If we ought not to eat common bread with him, much leſſe to joyne with him in the Sacrament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is in our owne power to have familiarity or common ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety with him or not: but not in our power to eat or not to eat with him at the Sacrament; if the Church be remiſſe in exerciſe of diſcipline, the remedy to be uſed in this caſe, the Apoſtle preſcribes in the laſt clauſe of the Chapter: Therefore put away from you that wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: he ſaith not, if the Church be remiſſe, and that he be not put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, come not to the table of the Lord. The Text beareth no ſuch weight that way, but that in diſcharge of my duty, I ought to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the ordinance, unleſſe it were in my power to caſt him out, but of this heretofore.</p>
               <p n="19">19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye ſeparate, ſaith the Lord, and touch no uncleane thing, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you.</p>
               <p>This Text and that of <hi>Revelation</hi> 18.4. are the two maſter-pieces of all their Scriptures: I will ſpeake firſt to that, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. where wee muſt conſider, firſt, who are to ſeparate; ſecondly from whom they are to ſeparate; thirdly, what are the uncleane things there not to bee touched.</p>
               <p>Firſt, they that are to ſeparate, are the beleeving <hi>Corinthians,</hi> men converted from Heatheniſh and Idolatrous cuſtomes and ſervices, to faith in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they muſt ſeparate from Infidels, men deſtitute of the knowledge of Chriſt, and men voyd of faith, men not profeſſing Chriſt, palpable Idolaters, as appeares in the foregoing verſes. What fellowſhip hath righteouſneſſe with unrighteouſneſſe, or what concord hath Chriſt with <hi>Beliall?</hi> the beleever with the infidell; or what agree-hath the Temple of God with Idols?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the uncleane things from which they are to ſeparate are their Idols and prophane ſacrifices: and truely if in the viſible face of our aſſemblies Chriſt were not profeſſed, his ordinances diſpenſed, if the ordinances were ſuperſtitious and Idolatrous in their nature and inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and heatheniſh Gods were worſhipped by us, it were indeed good reaſon for all Gods people, all that beleeve in Chriſt to ſeparate, but that this place tolerates any man to ſeparate from ordinances in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by Chriſt and miniſtred in aſſemblies profeſſing Chriſt, and where are many beleevers met together in the name of Chriſt; this I finde no warrant for though there may be many corrupt members ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:155268:29"/> in and about them, the ordinances remaine the ordinances of Chriſt, notwithſtanding prophane men have to doe in the diſpenſation of them: <hi>Elies</hi> ſonnes were wicked, but the ordinances kept their owne nature and uſe to Gods people that came duly prepared to them. If thoſe that pleade for ſeparation can make it appeare that in all the booke of God there is any one place to countenance or warrant a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from ordinances of the Lord Chriſts owne inſtitution, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the evill managing of them, and corrupt men imployed about them, then they ſay ſomething; but becauſe Scripture commands Gods people to ſeparate from the Aſſemblies of heathens, which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped falſe Gods, as the Sunne, Moone, &amp;c. and ſuch as obſerved Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous cuſtomes and practiſes in ordinances invented of their owne braine, not inſtituted by Chriſt, this can be no warrant for Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to ſeparate from the Ordinances of Chriſt. If they ſhall yet ſay, the corrupt managing and diſpenſation of them make the ordinances un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane and Idolatrous; I hope there is formerly ſpoken enough to give ſatisfaction to that, where it is proved lawfull to joyne in mixt aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and the unlawfulneſſe of ſeparation.<note place="margin">Rev. 18 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> As for this portion of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, where it is ſaid, Come out of [her] my people that yee be not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of her ſinnes, and that yee receive not of her plagues.</p>
               <p>We muſt underſtand what is meant by this word [her,] and if we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the 17. and 18. Chapter of this booke of <hi>Revelation,</hi> wee ſhall plainely finde it to be the ſcarlet Whore, the Pope of Rome, ſo all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors, the whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that mother of harlots, and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the earth. Chap. 16.19. And great <hi>Babylon</hi> came in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance before God to give unto her the cup of the wine of the fiercenes of the wrath of God. Chap. 17. Verſ. 1. Come hither, ſaith the Angell to Saint <hi>John,</hi> and I will ſhew thee the judgement of the great Whore, that fits upon many waters, with whom the Kings of the earth have committed fornication, and read, &amp;c. read I ſay the fourth, fifth, ſixt, ſeventh and ſo to the end of that Chapter. Now in the eighteenth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Lord by St. <hi>John</hi> foretells the fall and deſtruction of this great whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> by reaſon of her great abominations; and gives an exhortation for Gods people to come out of her, ſuch as have joyned with her in her ſins, leſt they do alſo partake of her plagues. What war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant this gives men to ſeparate from the ordinances of God, and the publique aſſemblies of Gods people exerciſed in and about the worſhip of God I know not, we all know that <hi>Rome</hi> is the very ſeate of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:155268:30"/> both for the matter and manner of their worſhip, their doctrine falſe in fundamentalls, more corrupt then Heathens and Pagans; there is no ordinance of Chriſt among them, onely the Word is preached in an erroneous and falſe way to the people to ſeduce and betray them from Chriſt to Antichriſt; they have ordained Sacraments of their owne, worſhips of their owne, nay in a Scripture ſenſe, gods of their owne; from the aſſemblies of theſe Idolaters Gods people muſt ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, not from publique Congregations of Gods worſhip, for as I have ſpoken at large, with us are the ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, the Word of God taught ſufficiently to ſalvation in all that beleeve; we obſerve no other ordinances but what Chriſt hath inſtituted and ordained, but it is impoſſible for any man to come to life and ſalvation by their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous worſhips; though the Lord may have his number amongſt them which have not bowed the knee to <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all,</hi> yet theſe were never converted by the falſe worſhips, ordinances and inventions, but by ſome extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary or immediat bleſſing beſtowed upon them from the reading of the Scriptures, &amp;c. and inſpiration of his Spirit, &amp;c. for Satan never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets children to God,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.25.</note> nor Antichriſt convert men to Chriſt, A king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome divided againſt it ſelfe cannot ſtand. And thus having very briefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken concerning thoſe places of Scripture alledged by thoſe that plead for a ſeparation, according as my weake talent and ſhort time will permit: I will ſhut up with the fifth and laſt thing I intended and promiſed to ſpeake to, which is onely to give a few words to avoyde miſtakes; for I earneſtly deſire not to offend the conſcience of the weakeſt Chriſtian, or to bring upon my ſelfe that aſperſion which ſome prejudicately would caſt upon me. For I call God to witneſſe that according to that poore l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght God hath given me, I have not beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rious to any knowne place of Scripture or winked at any knowne truth in this diſcourſe, but have as earneſtly deſired and unpartially indeavoured to convince my owne heart of the truth of this point of ſo great concernement, and that makes ſo great difference among Gods people, as for the informing of any other to whom I am in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure engaged by way of promiſe or private intereſt.</p>
               <p>Therefore I deſire to deliver my ſelfe plainely as I can, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I have ſpoken upon this ſubject is neither to dignifie my owne opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, nor to maintaine or pleade for any corruption or abuſe in our Church aſſemblies, or diſpenſation of the ordinances: for while I ſay it is unlawfull to ſeparate from ſuch aſſemblies, for reaſons formerly
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:155268:30"/> given, yet I ſay not it is lawfull for corrupt and prophane men to bee admitted to the Sacrament, onely I have deſired to informe my ſelfe and others how and in what manner they may ſafely joyne and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the ordinances of life and ſalvation to their comfort, though thoſe in authority be remiſſe in the exerciſe of diſcipline, and ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt in their offices and truſt repoſed in them.</p>
               <p>But I doe earneſtly deſire to perſwade and ſtirre up my ſelfe and all Gods people in all our ſeverall addreſſements to God in prayer wee would make this on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeciall part of our deſires, that God would purge the Church of all abuſes both in doctrine and manners, and ſettle the ordinances amongſt us in their power and purity: and I deſire not only that Gods people ſhould pray againſt theſe corruptions, but mourne for the continuance of them, and every one according to the bounds and limits of his place and calling to ſhow his utter diſlike of them in all lawfull wayes, though not by ſeparating, which I hope ſufficiently appeares to bee unlawfull, the premiſes conſidered: and truely this I have done for theſe reaſons following.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to ſatisfie my ſelfe and others that were doubtfull in this point of joyning in mixt aſſemblies lawfully.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to make up the breaches and avoyd diſſention &amp; diviſion which Satan is apt to make between not onely carnall men and godly m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, but betweene the godly themſelves, which is that that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends in the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.3.</note> and tells them plainely it was an evidence of their carnality; and this alſo hee earneſtly exhorts them to by the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10</note> that they would all ſpeake the ſame thing, and that there be no diviſion among them, but be perfectly joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together in one and the ſame judgement, and in <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treates them to marke ſuch as cauſe diviſion, and to avoyd them, have no unneceſſary ſociety with them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that the enemies mouthes may be ſtopped, not onely the Papiſts, who as I formerly ſaid, ſhoot this as their maine thunderbolt againſt our Religion, the diverſity of opinions, but alſo our prophane looſe Proteſtants, nay even our civill honeſt men, who take occaſion from hence to reproach the wayes and people of God, of which wee have too much wofull experience; yea and it is a maine ſtumbling blocke in the wayes of many weake ones that might otherwiſe bee won to Chriſt, even the deviſions among Gods people,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.15.</note> whilſt Gods people by an even and peaceably walking, following the truth in love, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:155268:31"/> by keeping the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.3.</note> might adorne the Goſpell, and by their godly converſation incourage others to come in. And now in all that I have ſaid having declared my owne judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which I ſhall ever carry in my hand, and lay at the feet of him that ſhall give mee further light, though I deſire not to meddle with too many doubtfull diſputations, my time nor abilities affording it: I beſeech the Lord to perſwade our hearts what is good and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to him, and how to walke in all well pleaſing before him, to whom be all honour and glory for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:155268:31"/>
            <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt many friendly ſolicitations I had for the publiſhing this Treatiſe, I met with one whom I made acquainted with my intentions, that thought it not convenient at this time by reaſon as be conceived it would give ſome advantage to our wicked Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants to cheriſh in themſelves their evill thoughts of the Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h and people of God for their diviſion, by reaſon this booke alſo in diverſe p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aces of it reprehendeth the like miſdemeanours in the Church, which the Papiſts and our prophane ones ſo much caſt in the face of our Religion; and truely before I brought it to the preſſe, I debated the buſineſſe with my ſelfe, whether the premiſes conſidered, I ought rather in conſcience to bring it forth for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Church and people of God, or to conceale it for this ſuppoſed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage: and being very willing to remove all ſcruples from their tender conſcience, I thought good briefely to ſet downe the reaſons and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which inforced the birth of that which otherwiſe had beene buried in oblivion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I conſidered many had laboured with mee to have it made publike, and but one onely that objected any thing againſt it, and that onely for the time preſent be thought not convenient.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I conſidered the fuller of diſtractions the Church and State is, the more need is there to haſten forth ſuch a ſubject as this is.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that we ought to have a farre more high eſteeme of the ſatisfying the conſcience of the weake Chriſtian, and to have a greater care to ſettle the diviſions which are in the Church, then to trouble our ſelves with the evill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of the wicked.</p>
            <p>Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rthly, there is nothing made knowne herein either to Papiſts or Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants that they can take the leaſt advantage, but what they already know they know too well by our rents and ſchiſmes in the Church that wee are divided, whether any man ſhould indeavour the unitie thereof yea or no; ſurely w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhould not be aſhamed to make peace betweene neighbours, though ſome others doe thereby take notice of the difference betweene them, much leſſe ought wee to neglect to indeavour the quiet of the Church and people of God, although
<pb facs="tcp:155268:32"/> even hereby ſome men take notice of the diſtractions in it.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, the beſt way to convince the adverſaries of truth is to ſide with them ſo farre as they ſpeake the truth, neither ought wee to bee aſhamed to ſpeake that which is a truth, although the prophaneſt wretch in the world ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld ſpeake the ſame, for by the ſame reaſon, becauſe the Devill acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Chriſt to bee the Sonne of God the Diſciples ſhould have denied him.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, men of prophane and malignant ſpirits never trouble themſelves much with bookes of Divinity, eſpecially in theſe times wherein nothing ſells but State matters; I dare preſume where there is one malignant buyes this Booke to abuſe it, twentie honeſt men will buy it for their benefit.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, the neglect of treating upon this and the like ſubject is a maine cauſe of the diviſions of the Church, there not being one of a hundred that ſpend their time in publike or private, by word or writing this way, and if the conſciences of Gods people bee ſatisfied in this point, there will conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently be more peace in the Church, and leſſe ground of ſcandall; the cauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing removed the effect muſt needs ceaſe.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, if every man ſhould be ſilent this way, it would be a tacit juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the prepoſterous proceedings of them that make ſuch diſturbances in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like aſſemblies, which no honeſt man dare doe.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, whatſoever truth of Gods Word there is, that concernes his glory, and his Churches welfare, to bee declared, this ought not to be ſmothered for ſome ſeeming diſadvantage.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10.</hi> If we muſt write nor ſpeak no truths that wicked men will carpe at, and draw falſe concluſions from, truely many precious truthes would lie in obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, as that of free Grace, of Predeſtination, and many other of like concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nay wee ſee by experience in generall how the ſtanding ſo much for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation hath cauſed many malignants to ſpend their wits, wealth, time and ſtrength to oppoſe it.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11.</hi> There is not a word of encouragement in all the Booke to countenance wicked men in their ſinfull approaching the Lords Table, although Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may warrantably participate notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12.</hi> If Chriſtians would reſt ſatisfied in this point, and waite upon God in the uſe of the meanes of grace, till the Lord by a lawfull power perfect the worke of reformation; this would be both a great forwarding to the worke, and the beſt way to ſtop the mouth of the adverſaries of peace and truth.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13.</hi> So long as the diviſions of the Church are continued, and eſpecially if countenanced by ſilence, it gives the enemy cauſe to blaſpheme the name of God, and ſpeake evill of his wayes, farre more then ſuch indeavours for peace as this is or any way can doe.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb facs="tcp:155268:32"/>
               <hi>14.</hi> The worſt they can ſay or ſee from hence is that the Church is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, this they ſay and ſee too apparent, the more neede of a ſpeedy reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15.</hi> If bookes of this nature give advantage to Papiſts and malignants to cry out upon the diviſions of the Church, how much more thoſe hundreds that maintaine a ſeparation and ſo occaſion diviſion?</p>
            <p n="16">
               <hi>16.</hi> If this Booke maintaine malignant Tenets, ſo doth the Author, and as farre as it doth, and then it can be no ſcandall at all to the people of God, it will be conceived the worke of a malignant; but I ſee no cauſe if it have <hi>Jacobs</hi> voyce, why it ſhould have <hi>Eſaues</hi> garment put upon it; it may peradventure meete with the like entertainment from ſome particulars, as the Sunne and Moone doth in their courſe; there is a kind of bird that loves not the Sunne, and a kinde of beaſt that will barke at the Moone, yet the Planets themſelves of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable uſe to the whole Creation; even ſo ſome one or other may bee offended here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, that is no true friend to light, truth or peace; but I am comforted in this, what I have written is well bottomed upon God Word, intended for his glory, and the peace of his Church. And I am confident of this, that while wicked men like Serpents ſucke poyſon out of the pureſt grape, Gods people like the Bee will draw bony out of this <hi>Bramble Berry,</hi> for whoſe ſakes I have publiſhed it, the Lord make it ſucceſſefull.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
